<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Preserving Holiness</title><link href="https://preserving-holiness.github.io/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="https://preserving-holiness.github.io/feeds/all.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>https://preserving-holiness.github.io/</id><updated>2025-07-12T12:58:00-04:00</updated><entry><title>Preparing Your Heart for the Holy Spirit</title><link href="https://preserving-holiness.github.io/preparing-your-heart-for-the-holy-spirit.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2025-07-12T12:58:00-04:00</published><updated>2025-07-12T12:58:00-04:00</updated><author><name>A W Tozer &amp; ChatGPT</name></author><id>tag:preserving-holiness.github.io,2025-07-12:/preparing-your-heart-for-the-holy-spirit.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Claim Your Birthright - The Spirit-filled life is not optional or for a select few. When Christ died, this fullness became available to every believer. 2. Welcome Him as Friend, Not Foe -...&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Claim Your Birthright&lt;/strong&gt;  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Spirit-filled life is not optional or for a select few. When Christ died, this fullness became available to every believer.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Welcome Him as Friend, Not Foe&lt;/strong&gt;  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Holy Spirit isn’t strange or scary. He’s Jesus’ presence in you—gentle, loving, and good.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Surrender Everything&lt;/strong&gt;  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s not just about blessings. Are you ready to let go of your plans, pride, and control? True filling requires handing over every area of life.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Long for More Than Basics&lt;/strong&gt;  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Prayers, Bible study, and good deeds are vital—but they’re just the start. Crave deeper fellowship, purity, strength for service, and victory over temptation.  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Steps to Receive the Holy Spirit&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Offer Your Whole Self&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
   Present your body, thoughts, emotions, and will to God as an act of worship (Rom. 12:1–2).  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ask in Faith&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
   Simple, believing prayer is enough: “Ask, and it will be given you” (Luke 11:9–13).  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Live in Obedience&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
   The Spirit is promised to those who follow Christ’s commands (Acts 5:32).  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Trust His Promise&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
   Just as you received salvation by faith, receive the Spirit’s fullness the same way (Gal. 3:2).  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you believe it’s your right, yearn for His fullness, and take these steps with simple trust, the Holy Spirit will come and fill you. Tonight, as we sing “The Comforter Has Come,” open your heart, ask, and expect Him to move.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Books"></category><category term="Book-Summaries"></category><category term="Books"></category><category term="Chapter-Summaries"></category></entry><entry><title>The Promise of the Father: A Condensed Reflection</title><link href="https://preserving-holiness.github.io/the-promise-of-the-father.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2025-07-12T12:54:00-04:00</published><updated>2025-07-12T12:54:00-04:00</updated><author><name>A W Tozer and ChatGPT</name></author><id>tag:preserving-holiness.github.io,2025-07-12:/the-promise-of-the-father.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Opening Promise Jesus tells His disciples in Luke 24:49, "I send the promise of my Father upon you," pointing back to Joel's prophecy that God would pour out His Spirit on all people. Three Stages of the Promise 1. Promise Phase (John the Baptist to Resurrection) - Disciples knew Jesus...&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Opening Promise&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
Jesus tells His disciples in Luke 24:49, "I send the promise of my Father upon you," pointing back to Joel's prophecy that God would pour out His Spirit on all people.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Three Stages of the Promise&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
1. &lt;strong&gt;Promise Phase (John the Baptist to Resurrection)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
   - Disciples knew Jesus personally—His teachings, death, and resurrection.&lt;br&gt;
   - Jesus built their hope for a new power beyond what they already experienced.&lt;br&gt;
   - They expected an "outpouring" of divine energy they had not yet seen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Preparation Phase (Resurrection to Pentecost)&lt;/strong&gt;  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;After rising, Jesus commanded the disciples to "tarry" in Jerusalem.  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Their work paused so they could receive what had been promised.  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Though seemingly idle, they grew in unity and expectation, gathering 120 believers in prayer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Realization Phase (Pentecost)&lt;/strong&gt;  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The Holy Spirit arrived like a rushing wind and tongues of fire (Acts 2).  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Peter describes this as God "shedding forth" the Spirit—an overflow beyond their hopes.  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Believers gained new, inner proof of faith: the Spirit's direct witness in their hearts.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;External vs. Internal Evidence&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
- &lt;strong&gt;External Proofs&lt;/strong&gt;: Scriptures, John the Baptist’s testimony, God’s miracles, and Christ’s works all point to Jesus but rely on logic and outside signs.&lt;br&gt;
- &lt;strong&gt;Internal Witness&lt;/strong&gt;: Only the Holy Spirit gives an immediate, living assurance—like feeling alive—free from the need for argument.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Impact of the Holy Spirit&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
- &lt;strong&gt;Transformation&lt;/strong&gt;: Converts in distant lands, unfamiliar with Christian logic, believe and change by the Spirit’s power alone.&lt;br&gt;
- &lt;strong&gt;Emotion and Joy&lt;/strong&gt;: Early believers experienced vibrant emotion and spiritual delight, qualities lacking in many modern services.&lt;br&gt;
- &lt;strong&gt;Authority&lt;/strong&gt;: Freed from fear and doubt, they spoke with boldness rooted in life, not mere logic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ongoing Promise Today&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
Some claim the Spirit’s coming was a one-time event only for the first church. But if the fullness received by the apostles doesn’t apply to us, it’s like eating Peter’s meal in A.D. 33 and expecting it to nourish us now—impossible across centuries and seas.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Questions for Reflection&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
- Is the Father’s promise solely for first-century Christians, or must each believer be filled today?&lt;br&gt;
- Does "the new birth" and Spirit’s fullness happen once for all, or must we personally receive them?&lt;br&gt;
- Do we have what the early Church enjoyed, or have our expectations fallen short?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;A Call to Seek&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
Jesus urged His followers to wait because the Spirit’s coming would mean the difference between failure and success. The early Church said, "They were amazed," because God gave more than He promised.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Invitation&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
If today’s faith feels weaker than what was promised, admit the gap. Seek Scripture, prayer, obedience, and faith so that the Father’s promise may be yours in full—beyond expectation, just as in the first Pentecost.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Books"></category><category term="Book-Summaries"></category><category term="Books"></category><category term="Chapter-Summaries"></category></entry><entry><title>[Who Is the Holy Spirit?]</title><link href="https://preserving-holiness.github.io/who-is-the-holy-spirit.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2025-07-09T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2025-07-09T00:00:00-04:00</updated><author><name>A W Tozer and ChatGPT</name></author><id>tag:preserving-holiness.github.io,2025-07-09:/who-is-the-holy-spirit.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;--- &lt;strong&gt;Chapter 1: Who Is the Holy Spirit? (Abridged)&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;strong&gt;1. Defining “Spirit”&lt;/strong&gt; When we speak of spirit here, we aren’t talking about courage, temperament, or energy. Spirit is real—another mode of being, just as real as matter. While matter has weight, shape, and occupies space, spirit can penetrate everything—bodies, thoughts,...&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Chapter 1: Who Is the Holy Spirit? (Abridged)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;1. Defining “Spirit”&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
When we speak of spirit here, we aren’t talking about courage, temperament, or energy. Spirit is real—another mode of being, just as real as matter. While matter has weight, shape, and occupies space, spirit can penetrate everything—bodies, thoughts, even other spirit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2. What Is the Holy Spirit?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
The Holy Spirit is a divine Being existing in this same nonmaterial mode. No weight, size, or color—but no less real. He is not mere enthusiasm, genius, or inspiration. He is a Person: with will, intelligence, feeling, and the power to love, hear, and speak.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;3. Biblical and Historical Witness&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
- &lt;strong&gt;Creeds:&lt;/strong&gt; The Nicene Creed (AD 325) calls Him “Lord and Giver of life” to be worshiped with Father and Son. The Athanasian Creed repeats: “Such as the Father is, such is the Holy Ghost,” implying equality with the other Persons of the Trinity.
- &lt;strong&gt;Hymns:&lt;/strong&gt; Writers pray to the Holy Ghost with divine titles: “power divine,” “cleanse this guilty heart,” “reign supreme.” Such prayers can only be addressed to God.
- &lt;strong&gt;Scripture:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
  - &lt;strong&gt;Omnipresence:&lt;/strong&gt; “Whither shall I go from Your Spirit?” (Psalm 139:7) – only God is everywhere.&lt;br&gt;
  - &lt;strong&gt;Eternity:&lt;/strong&gt; Hebrews 9:14 speaks of the “eternal Spirit,” a quality no created being has.&lt;br&gt;
  - &lt;strong&gt;Baptismal Formula:&lt;/strong&gt; Matthew 28:19 instructs baptism “in the name of the Father, Son, and Holy Spirit,” placing the Spirit on equal footing with God.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;4. Why It Matters&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
Many Christians accept the doctrine of the Spirit without knowing or experiencing His power. Truths can lie dormant if we don’t teach and apply them. Just as belief in healing does little unless practiced, belief in the Spirit’s fullness does little unless we seek it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;5. What the Spirit Is Like&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
Everywhere, always present—He is indistinguishable in character from the Father and the Son. If Jesus walked among us today, we’d feel welcome, loved, safe. That is the Spirit: the same love, kindness, and warmth we find in Christ.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Invitation&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
Believe not just in doctrine but in living reality. Invite the Holy Spirit to fill your heart, transforming you from within with divine presence, power, and peace.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Books"></category><category term="Book-Summaries"></category><category term="Books"></category><category term="Chapter-Summaries"></category></entry><entry><title>Preface to How to be Filled with the Holy Spirit, by A. W. Tozer</title><link href="https://preserving-holiness.github.io/preface-to-how-to-be-filled-with-the-holy-spirit-by-a-w-tozer.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2025-07-05T18:58:00-04:00</published><updated>2025-07-05T18:58:00-04:00</updated><author><name>A. W. Tozer &amp; Gemini 2.5 Flash</name></author><id>tag:preserving-holiness.github.io,2025-07-05:/preface-to-how-to-be-filled-with-the-holy-spirit-by-a-w-tozer.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Preface to the Book.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Title: Preface to How to be Filled with the Holy Spirit, by A. W. Tozer
Date: 2025-07-05
Status: published
Category: Books
Tags: Books, Book-Summaries, Chapter-Summaries
Author: A. W. Tozer &amp;amp; Gemini 2.5 Flash
Summary: Preface to the Book.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Understanding the Holy Spirit&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This book, published by Moody Publishers, is a collection of sermons on the Holy Spirit.  Authored by A.W.T., it aims to guide believers towards a deeper understanding and relationship with the Holy Spirit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Key Features:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Content:&lt;/strong&gt; The book explores the identity of the Holy Spirit, the promise of the Father, how to be filled with the Holy Spirit, and how to cultivate a deeper companionship with Him.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Style:&lt;/strong&gt; Written in a conversational, informal style reflecting its origins as a series of sermons.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Purpose:&lt;/strong&gt; To help Christian believers develop a closer relationship with the Holy Spirit.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Copyright:&lt;/strong&gt; © 1952, 1992, 2001, 2016 by Moody Bible Institute of Chicago.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;ISBN:&lt;/strong&gt; 978-1-60066-799-2&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The proceeds from the book support Moody Bible Institute students.  The author notes that the book's informal style is a result of its sermon origins.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Books"></category><category term="Books"></category><category term="Book-Summaries"></category><category term="Chapter-Summaries"></category></entry><entry><title>Our Declaration of Online Status</title><link href="https://preserving-holiness.github.io/our-declaration-of-online-status.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2025-07-04T11:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2025-07-04T11:00:00-04:00</updated><author><name>nameless</name></author><id>tag:preserving-holiness.github.io,2025-07-04:/our-declaration-of-online-status.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Site Online, All systems operational, except the custom domain.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="An example image" src="https://preserving-holiness.github.io/images/sample-image.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Welcome one and all! This site will hopefully start producing content within the next few days, and hopefully it is appreciated, not now, maybe never further than arms' reach.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;May God be Praised, we've come this far.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;-me&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Updates"></category><category term="updates"></category><category term="admin"></category></entry></feed>