<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Preserving Holiness</title><link href="https://preservingholiness.github.io/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="https://preservingholiness.github.io/feeds/all.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>https://preservingholiness.github.io/</id><updated>2024-07-29T18:14:00-04:00</updated><entry><title>Our Mission</title><link href="https://preservingholiness.github.io/our-mission.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2024-07-29T18:14:00-04:00</published><updated>2024-07-29T18:14:00-04:00</updated><author><name>nameless</name></author><id>tag:preservingholiness.github.io,2024-07-29:/our-mission.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;h1&gt;Our Mission&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our mission on this tiny blog is to bring the best of Old-Time Fire and Brimstone preaching to a modern, but no less carnal, audience. We utilize the best of bleeding edge technologies in AI to bring you the most unbiased, most poignant renderings of the documents of …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;h1&gt;Our Mission&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our mission on this tiny blog is to bring the best of Old-Time Fire and Brimstone preaching to a modern, but no less carnal, audience. We utilize the best of bleeding edge technologies in AI to bring you the most unbiased, most poignant renderings of the documents of the past which hold our truth for the world, though sometimes harder for our modern audience, or even our youths or gradeschool children to understand.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is a wild, untamed wilderness on the internet known as Reddit, a forum site of sorts, where people often ask others to "Explain X topic to me like I'm five years old". Those of us who regularly read and understand the King James Version of the Bible take for granted the amount of archaic English literature we are consuming on a daily basis, and therefore, our comfort level with the Thesaurus. To illustrate my point, let me give you some chilling facts about literacy in the United States straight from Gemini 2.5 Pro (Google's Head-of-Pack AI).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Literacy and the US&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An estimated 21% of adults in the United States are considered to have low literacy skills, falling into the category of illiterate or functionally illiterate, according to the National Center for Education Statistics (NCES).This translates to approximately 43 million Americans who may struggle with daily tasks such as reading a newspaper, understanding instructions on a medicine bottle, or filling out a job application.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.thenationalliteracyinstitute.com/post/literacy-statistics-2024-2025-where-we-are-nowhttps:/"&gt;Source 1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://risingtide.ua.edu/education/statewide-ua-literacy-center/"&gt;Source 2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The definition of literacy, however, extends beyond a simple "can or cannot read" binary. The data reveals different levels of literacy proficiency, with a substantial number of adults lacking the skills needed to thrive in an increasingly complex and information-rich society.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Further analysis from various sources paints a more detailed picture of the issue. While the 21% figure for functional illiteracy is widely cited, other statistics highlight the varying degrees of reading ability. For instance, a &lt;strong&gt;staggering 54%&lt;/strong&gt; of American adults—&lt;strong&gt;roughly 130 million people&lt;/strong&gt;—have a literacy proficiency below the &lt;strong&gt;sixth-grade&lt;/strong&gt; level, according to the Barbara Bush Foundation for Family Literacy. This indicates that while they may have basic reading skills, they lack the ability to comprehend and analyze more complex texts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://map.barbarabush.org/"&gt;Barbara Bush's Literacy Map&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;More recent data from the NCES, released in late 2024, indicates a concerning trend. &lt;strong&gt;The percentage of adults performing at the lowest literacy levels (Level 1 or below) has increased from 19% in 2017 to 28% in 2023.&lt;/strong&gt; This suggests a growing challenge in ensuring all citizens have the foundational skills necessary for full participation in the economy and civic life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://nces.ed.gov/surveys/piaac/2023/national_results.asp"&gt;Source 3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Need anything more be stated? &lt;strong&gt;No.&lt;/strong&gt; For in this mission, we see it is &lt;strong&gt;"To do, or die trying"&lt;/strong&gt;. Bringing the Gospel to the common people was the reason our beloved KJV came into existence. We are committing no crimes in repurposing content with obscure meanings into more practical language. This is why there is a Fair Use clause in US Copyright Law. We plan to abide by it here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Our Pledge&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The pledge I here make to those who shall follow me is this: I shall promote the doctrine of "Holiness, whithout which no man shall see the Lord." I will strive to the best of my ability to not stray too far left or too far right in this endeavor. My goal is to keep my personal life and humanity out of the equation as much as I can.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="misc"></category></entry></feed>