<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Preserving Holiness - Books</title><link href="https://preserving-holiness.github.io/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="https://preserving-holiness.github.io/feeds/books.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>https://preserving-holiness.github.io/</id><updated>2025-07-12T14:49:00-04:00</updated><entry><title>Baptisms of the Spirit Under the Old and New Dispensations – a Condensed Overview</title><link href="https://preserving-holiness.github.io/baptisms-of-the-spirit-under-the-old-and-new-dispensations-a-condensed-overview.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2025-07-12T14:49:00-04:00</published><updated>2025-07-12T14:49:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Asa Mahan &amp; ChatGPT</name></author><id>tag:preserving-holiness.github.io,2025-07-12:/baptisms-of-the-spirit-under-the-old-and-new-dispensations-a-condensed-overview.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Introduction: Joel’s prophecy (Joel 2:28–29) foretells a universal outpouring of the Spirit; John clarifies that the Holy Spirit’s full gift awaited Christ’s glorification (John 7:39). Old Testament Baptisms: - Enoch and Early Saints: In varying degrees, individuals like Enoch enjoyed communion with God’s Spirit. - Abraham and Jacob: Each experienced...&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Introduction:&lt;/strong&gt;
Joel’s prophecy (Joel 2:28–29) foretells a universal outpouring of the Spirit; John clarifies that the Holy Spirit’s full gift awaited Christ’s glorification (John 7:39).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Old Testament Baptisms:&lt;/strong&gt;
- &lt;strong&gt;Enoch and Early Saints:&lt;/strong&gt; In varying degrees, individuals like Enoch enjoyed communion with God’s Spirit.
- &lt;strong&gt;Abraham and Jacob:&lt;/strong&gt; Each experienced transformative encounters (e.g., Abraham’s assured faith in God’s promise; Jacob’s vision at Bethel).
- &lt;strong&gt;Moses:&lt;/strong&gt; Exchanged the Spirit’s power for intimate knowledge of God’s character—Moses’ radiant face after Sinai marks a new inward communion.
- &lt;strong&gt;Seventy Elders:&lt;/strong&gt; God shared Moses’ Spirit so they could prophesy—true prophecy flows from the Spirit’s illumination, not merely future-telling (Numbers 11).
- &lt;strong&gt;Saul and Others:&lt;/strong&gt; Kings, prophets, even unlikely recipients (Saul, Saul’s messengers, Balaam) received temporary Spirit-baptisms that conferred speaking God’s truth and specific gifts.
- &lt;strong&gt;Elisha:&lt;/strong&gt; A lasting double portion of Elijah’s Spirit inaugurated his prophetic ministry (2 Kings 2).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;New Testament Precursors:&lt;/strong&gt;
- &lt;strong&gt;Zacharias, Elizabeth, Mary:&lt;/strong&gt; Each filled with the Holy Spirit before Pentecost, echoing Old Testament patterns but pointing ahead to greater realities (Luke 1).
- These experiences included joy, prophecy, magnifying God, and foreshadowed Pentecost’s power.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Great Difference:&lt;/strong&gt;
1. &lt;strong&gt;Universality:&lt;/strong&gt; Old anointings were rare and for individuals; New promises the Spirit to &lt;em&gt;all&lt;/em&gt; believers (Joel’s “all flesh,” Acts 2).
2. &lt;strong&gt;Permanency:&lt;/strong&gt; Once temporary, now an abiding Comforter who remains with the Church (John 14:16).
3. &lt;strong&gt;Greater Power:&lt;/strong&gt; Old saints saw partial glories; Christ’s life and resurrection fully reveal God’s character. The Spirit now unveils Christ’s glory in us, bringing life, sanctification, and joy beyond earlier experiences.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Scriptural Testimony:&lt;/strong&gt;
- &lt;strong&gt;Peter:&lt;/strong&gt; Prophets longed to know the Spirit’s timing—Pentecost fulfilled their prophecies (1 Peter 1:10–12).
- &lt;strong&gt;Hebrews:&lt;/strong&gt; Old saints received promises by faith but awaited our fuller blessings (Hebrews 11:39–40).
- &lt;strong&gt;John:&lt;/strong&gt; The Spirit in its New Testament fullness was not yet given until after Christ’s glorification (John 7:39).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Implications for Today:&lt;/strong&gt;
- Believers now enjoy Spirit-baptisms equal to or surpassing the highest Old Testament experiences.
- The Church’s weakness stems from ignorance or neglect of Spirit-filled living.
- Restoring this doctrine and practice will usher in revival and prepare for the millennium.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Vision of the Future:&lt;/strong&gt;
Ezekiel’s river of life (Ezekiel 47) symbolizes the ever-growing, life-giving power of the Spirit in the Church, promising a golden age yet to come.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Conclusion:&lt;/strong&gt;
The Old and New Testament baptisms share a divine illumination and power, but the New dispensation’s gift of the Spirit—universal, permanent, and supremely powerful in Christ’s light—marks a transformative era for the Church. May every believer experience this all-empowering baptism. Amen.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Books"></category><category term="Book-Summaries"></category><category term="Books"></category><category term="Chapter-Summaries"></category></entry><entry><title>Doctrine of the Baptism of the Holy Ghost</title><link href="https://preserving-holiness.github.io/doctrine-of-the-baptism-of-the-holy-ghost.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2025-07-12T14:30:00-04:00</published><updated>2025-07-12T14:30:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Asa Mahan &amp; ChatGPT</name></author><id>tag:preserving-holiness.github.io,2025-07-12:/doctrine-of-the-baptism-of-the-holy-ghost.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Key Scripture Passages - Acts 19:1–6: Paul meets believers in Ephesus who haven’t heard of the Holy Ghost. After baptism in Jesus’ name and laying on of hands, they receive the Spirit, speak in tongues, and prophesy. - Acts 8:14–17: Peter and John pray for Samaritan believers to receive the...&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Key Scripture Passages&lt;/strong&gt;
- &lt;strong&gt;Acts 19:1–6&lt;/strong&gt;: Paul meets believers in Ephesus who haven’t heard of the Holy Ghost. After baptism in Jesus’ name and laying on of hands, they receive the Spirit, speak in tongues, and prophesy.
- &lt;strong&gt;Acts 8:14–17&lt;/strong&gt;: Peter and John pray for Samaritan believers to receive the Holy Ghost after baptism.
- &lt;strong&gt;Acts 10:44–47&lt;/strong&gt;: The Holy Ghost falls on Gentile listeners in Cornelius’ house; they speak in tongues and praise God.
- &lt;strong&gt;Ephesians 1:13–14; 3:14–21&lt;/strong&gt;: After believing, Christians are sealed with the Spirit as a guarantee of their inheritance and are strengthened in their inner being to know Christ’s love and fullness.
- &lt;strong&gt;John 7:38–39&lt;/strong&gt;: Believers receive the Spirit after Christ’s glorification, symbolized by rivers of living water.
- &lt;strong&gt;1 Corinthians 12&lt;/strong&gt;: The Spirit gives varied gifts—wisdom, healing, prophecy, tongues—to build up the Church.
- &lt;strong&gt;Acts 2 (Pentecost)&lt;/strong&gt;: The apostles unite in prayer, experience visible signs (wind, tongues), and are filled with the Spirit, speaking God’s word boldly.
- &lt;strong&gt;John 14–16&lt;/strong&gt;: Jesus promises another Helper (Comforter) who will dwell with believers forever, empowering and guiding them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Main Lessons&lt;/strong&gt;
1. &lt;strong&gt;Occurs After Conversion&lt;/strong&gt;: The Holy Ghost is given &lt;em&gt;after&lt;/em&gt; a person believes, completing their qualification for Christian service.
2. &lt;strong&gt;Empowers Believers&lt;/strong&gt;: This baptism equips Christians for tasks beyond natural ability—prayer, witness, endurance.
3. &lt;strong&gt;Visible Change&lt;/strong&gt;: Recipients and observers notice a distinct transformation—new boldness, spiritual gifts, praise.
4. &lt;strong&gt;Sought by Faith&lt;/strong&gt;: The Spirit is not automatic at conversion but promised to all who genuinely seek and wait in prayer.
5. &lt;strong&gt;Seal and Pledge&lt;/strong&gt;: The Spirit acts as God’s seal on believers, assuring them of forgiveness and inheritance until full redemption.
6. &lt;strong&gt;Fellowship and Fullness&lt;/strong&gt;: Through the Spirit, Christ and the Father dwell within, leading to deep fellowship, love, unity, joy, and peace.
7. &lt;strong&gt;Diverse Gifts&lt;/strong&gt;: Every believer receives spiritual gifts to serve the body of Christ; prophecy (spiritual truth) and tongues edify the Church.
8. &lt;strong&gt;Unity in the Church&lt;/strong&gt;: Baptism in the Spirit fosters unity and love, reflecting the oneness Jesus prayed for among his followers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Effects of the Baptism&lt;/strong&gt;
- &lt;strong&gt;Power&lt;/strong&gt;: Strength to pray, witness, and endure hardship ("run and not be weary").
- &lt;strong&gt;Insight&lt;/strong&gt;: Deeper understanding of Scripture and God’s truth.
- &lt;strong&gt;Assurance&lt;/strong&gt;: Conviction of sonship and eternal life ("we know we are of God").
- &lt;strong&gt;Fellowship&lt;/strong&gt;: Intimate communion with the Father, Son, and other believers.
- &lt;strong&gt;Joy and Peace&lt;/strong&gt;: Inner serenity, joy in trials, and hope that surpasses understanding.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Conditions to Receive&lt;/strong&gt;
1. &lt;strong&gt;Recognize the Promise&lt;/strong&gt;: Understand that this blessing is distinct from conversion, miracles, or other gifts.
2. &lt;strong&gt;Claim by Faith&lt;/strong&gt;: Believe firmly in God’s promise and righteousness through Jesus.
3. &lt;strong&gt;Seek Wholeheartedly&lt;/strong&gt;: Pray and wait in unity, like the early disciples at Pentecost.
4. &lt;strong&gt;Persevere&lt;/strong&gt;: Continue seeking until the Spirit fills the heart.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Conclusion&lt;/strong&gt;
The Baptism of the Holy Ghost is God’s highest gift in the New Covenant. It is essential for full Christian living, empowering believers with spiritual gifts, deep fellowship, and lasting change. Like the early Church, Christians today should understand, seek, and receive this promise to walk in the Spirit’s fullness.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Books"></category><category term="Book-Summaries"></category><category term="Books"></category><category term="Chapter-Summaries"></category></entry><entry><title>Christ’s Experience and Teachings on the Baptism of the Holy Ghost</title><link href="https://preserving-holiness.github.io/christs-experience-and-teachings-on-the-baptism-of-the-holy-ghost.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2025-07-12T13:57:00-04:00</published><updated>2025-07-12T13:57:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Asa Mahan &amp; ChatGPT</name></author><id>tag:preserving-holiness.github.io,2025-07-12:/christs-experience-and-teachings-on-the-baptism-of-the-holy-ghost.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;CHAPTER 2: CHRIST’S EXPERIENCE AND TEACHINGS ON THE BAPTISM OF THE HOLY GHOST 1. Divine and Human Forms in Christ - Jesus perfectly combined divine glory and human perfection: He is both our righteous Lord and our exemplar. - His spiritual life also depended on the Holy Spirit, just as...&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Divine and Human Forms in Christ&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Jesus perfectly combined divine glory and human perfection: He is both our righteous Lord and our exemplar.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;His spiritual life also depended on the Holy Spirit, just as ours does.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Prophetic Foundation&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Isaiah’s prophecies foretold that the Spirit would rest on the Messiah, granting wisdom, understanding, counsel, power, knowledge, and reverent awe (Isaiah 11:1–3; 42:1; 61:1).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These passages show Christ needed the Spirit’s anointing to fulfill His mission.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;New Testament Confirmation&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;John 3:34 emphasizes Christ’s speech and works came from the unlimited Spirit given to Him.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Christ’s frequent prayer and solitude reflect His dependence on divine power.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Christ’s Baptisms of the Spirit&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;At His baptism by John, Jesus prayed and received the Holy Spirit as a dove (Luke 3:21).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;After overcoming temptation, He returned “in the power of the Spirit” and began teaching boldly (Luke 4:14–15).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In Nazareth He read Isaiah 61, declared its fulfillment, and amazed the crowd by the Spirit’s power in His words.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Christ as Exemplar for Believers&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If even the sinless Son needed Spirit-baptism, we must likewise seek it before doing God’s work.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Christ asked the Father for the Spirit, showing us to ask, seek, and wait for “power from on high.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Christ’s Teaching on the Spirit&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Seek and Receive&lt;/strong&gt;: "Ask, seek, knock"—God gives the Holy Spirit to those who earnestly ask (Luke 11:9–13).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Personal Presence&lt;/strong&gt;: The Spirit is not mere influence but a permanent, personal Comforter abiding within believers (John 14:16–17).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Greater Blessings&lt;/strong&gt;: Believers receive richer gifts and understanding through the Spirit than through Christ’s earthly ministry (John 7:38–39).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Spirit’s Mission&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The Spirit teaches, reminds, guides into truth, glorifies Christ, testifies of Jesus, reproves the world, and reveals future things (John 14–16).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Through the Spirit we know God and Christ intimately, are transformed into Christ’s likeness, and bear spiritual fruit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Promises Through the Spirit&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Answered Prayer&lt;/strong&gt;: In Jesus’ name we may ask anything and receive it so joy may be full (John 16:23–24).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Divine Indwelling&lt;/strong&gt;: Father, Son, and Spirit dwell in us, uniting us with God (John 14:23; 17:21–23).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Peace and Joy&lt;/strong&gt;: We share Christ’s peace and joy as the Spirit abides in us (John 14:27; 17:13).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Greater Works&lt;/strong&gt;: Believers, empowered by the Spirit, will do even greater works than Jesus did (John 14:12).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Church’s Mission and Unity&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;All believers, as a Spirit-anointed body, are sent to labor for world salvation.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Each receives a special baptism of power for their unique mission, and together exhibits unity, love, and divine power that convinces the world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Christ’s Final Commission&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;After rising, Jesus breathed the Spirit on His disciples, commanded them to wait in Jerusalem for Spirit baptism, and then sent them out to preach with power (John 20:22; Acts 1:4–8).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Believers must both go in Christ’s name and tarry until they receive the Spirit’s power.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Key Takeaway:&lt;/strong&gt;
Jesus, though divine, modeled for us the need to seek and depend on the Holy Spirit. Through prophetic promise and His own teaching and example, He shows that Spirit-baptism is essential for empowering, guiding, and transforming believers to finish God’s work and bear witness to the world.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Books"></category><category term="Book-Summaries"></category><category term="Books"></category><category term="Chapter-Summaries"></category></entry><entry><title>God’s Pattern and the Path to Christian Character</title><link href="https://preserving-holiness.github.io/gods-pattern-and-the-path-to-christian-character.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2025-07-12T13:48:00-04:00</published><updated>2025-07-12T13:48:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Asa Mahan and ChatGPT</name></author><id>tag:preserving-holiness.github.io,2025-07-12:/gods-pattern-and-the-path-to-christian-character.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Scriptural Foundation Jesus promised that all who believe in Him would receive the Holy Spirit, making their lives overflow with spiritual power (John 7:37–39). Paul contrasted righteousness by faith with striving through law (Romans 9:30–32), showing that true growth depends on faith and the Spirit, not our own efforts. God’s...&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Scriptural Foundation&lt;/strong&gt;
Jesus promised that all who believe in Him would receive the Holy Spirit, making their lives overflow with spiritual power (John 7:37–39). Paul contrasted righteousness by faith with striving through law (Romans 9:30–32), showing that true growth depends on faith and the Spirit, not our own efforts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;God’s Divine Pattern&lt;/strong&gt;
Scripture outlines a clear model for the Christian character, called the “new man,” replacing our old, unrenewed nature:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Cleansed and Redeemed:&lt;/strong&gt; Freed from sin and idols, like the prophetic vision of eternal light and unending joy (cf. Isaiah, Joel’s outpouring).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Transformed by Glory:&lt;/strong&gt; Reflecting God’s image, growing from one level of glory to the next, filled with Christ’s love (2 Corinthians, Ephesians).  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Living in Fellowship:&lt;/strong&gt; Walking in God’s light, perfecting love, enjoying continual communion with Father and Son.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Empowered by the Spirit:&lt;/strong&gt; Joyful prayer, rivers of living water, strength in weakness, conquering all trials (Galatians, Romans).  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Spiritual Victory:&lt;/strong&gt; Growing faith and love, exercising power with God and people, shining as light and salt to the world.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This new life is not our achievement but God’s design—every trait springs from His Spirit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Source of True Transformation&lt;/strong&gt;
Every vital trait of the new man—vision of glory, fellowship with God, assurance of hope, love, joy, peace, spiritual victory—comes from the Holy Spirit:&lt;br&gt;
- He reveals Christ, testifies we are children of God, intercedes in prayer, and produces His fruit in us (Romans, Galatians).&lt;br&gt;
- He enables us to put off old habits and put on Christlike character by His power (Romans 8, Galatians 5).&lt;br&gt;
- Rivers of living water refer directly to the Spirit’s outpouring (John 7:39).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Order of God’s Work in the Believer&lt;/strong&gt;
1. &lt;strong&gt;Conviction and Faith:&lt;/strong&gt; The Spirit convicts us of sin, brings repentance, and leads us to trust Christ—this begins justification.&lt;br&gt;
2. &lt;strong&gt;Receiving the Spirit:&lt;/strong&gt; After believing, we are invited to ask for and receive the Spirit’s fullness. Apostles prayed that new believers might receive this powerful baptism (Acts 8:14–17; 19:1–6).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Seeking the Spirit in Faith&lt;/strong&gt;
Just as sinners ask for forgiveness, believers must ask God in faith for the Spirit’s fullness: “How much more will your Father give the Holy Spirit to those who ask Him!” (Luke 11:13). Jesus told His disciples to remain in Jerusalem until they were clothed with power from on high (Luke 24:49; Acts 1:4–8).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Consequences of Neglect&lt;/strong&gt;
Without this Spirit-baptism, Christian life falls short:&lt;br&gt;
- It remains powerless and hesitant, unable to reflect God’s pattern fully.&lt;br&gt;
- Historical examples: The twelve at Ephesus and Apollos were fervent believers but lacked fullness until they received the Spirit, limiting their impact (Acts 19; 18).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Two Views Compared&lt;/strong&gt;
1. &lt;strong&gt;Instantaneous at Conversion:&lt;/strong&gt; All the Spirit’s presence and power arrive at new birth.&lt;br&gt;
2. &lt;strong&gt;Distinct Promise after Belief:&lt;/strong&gt; Conversion brings initial indwelling; full empowerment comes afterward by asking in faith.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Why This Matters&lt;/strong&gt;
Teaching that nothing more is needed after salvation deprives believers of power, joy, and assurance. Misleading instruction sends them chasing shadows instead of seeking God’s promised fullness. Pastors and teachers must guide the flock to the clear word: ask, wait, and receive the promised baptism of the Spirit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;A Call to Seek&lt;/strong&gt;
This chapter aims to help readers know God’s pattern and attain it. If you have believed but never asked for the Spirit’s fullness, discover the better thing God offers. Read on, pray, and receive until filled with all the fullness of God.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Books"></category><category term="Book-Summaries"></category><category term="Books"></category><category term="Chapter-Summaries"></category></entry><entry><title>How to Cultivate the Spirit’s Companionship</title><link href="https://preserving-holiness.github.io/how-to-cultivate-the-spirits-companionship.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2025-07-12T13:04:00-04:00</published><updated>2025-07-12T13:04:00-04:00</updated><author><name>A W Tozer &amp; ChatGPT</name></author><id>tag:preserving-holiness.github.io,2025-07-12:/how-to-cultivate-the-spirits-companionship.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;“Can two walk together, except they be agreed?” — Amos 3:3 True fellowship with the Holy Spirit requires wholehearted agreement—an intentional, personal commitment to walk with Him daily. Many believers enjoy the benefits of salvation but hesitate to surrender fully, treating faith...&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Can two walk together, except they be agreed?” — Amos 3:3&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;True fellowship with the Holy Spirit requires wholehearted agreement—an intentional, personal commitment to walk with Him daily. Many believers enjoy the benefits of salvation but hesitate to surrender fully, treating faith like insurance rather than an intimate journey. This chapter calls those prepared—whose hearts long for heaven’s pull—to deepen their relationship with the Spirit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;1. Recognize the Spirit as a Living Person&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Holy Spirit is God’s third Person, capable of personal fellowship. Like any relationship, it grows through mutual engagement and affection.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;2. Be Engrossed with Jesus Christ&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Only when Jesus is glorified in your life will the Spirit overflow within you. Honor Christ by trusting, obeying, and glorifying Him fully; as you exalt Jesus, the Spirit responds with intimacy and power.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;3. Walk in Righteousness&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;True spirituality is inseparable from right living. Deny ungodliness, honor others, and maintain integrity. Fellowship with the Holy Spirit cannot thrive amid unholy behavior.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;4. Make Your Thoughts a Clean Sanctuary&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Your mind is the Spirit’s dwelling place. Choose thoughts of peace, charity, and holiness. Purge unclean ideas so your inner life reflects the beauty of God’s presence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;5. Seek Him in the Word&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Bible is the Spirit’s inspired revelation. Meditate deeply—without distractions—letting Scripture illuminate your heart. Replace superficial study with prayerful reflection on God’s Word.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;6. Cultivate the Art of Awareness&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Learn to recognize the Spirit’s presence in every moment: over breakfast, during work, or in quiet prayer. Like befriending a newborn, invest time daily. Soon even mundane tasks become sacred as Christ’s life flows through you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This summary preserves the heart of the original message while making it accessible.]&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Books"></category><category term="Book-Summaries"></category><category term="Books"></category><category term="Chapter-Summaries"></category></entry><entry><title>Preparing Your Heart for the Holy Spirit</title><link href="https://preserving-holiness.github.io/preparing-your-heart-for-the-holy-spirit.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2025-07-12T12:58:00-04:00</published><updated>2025-07-12T12:58:00-04:00</updated><author><name>A W Tozer &amp; ChatGPT</name></author><id>tag:preserving-holiness.github.io,2025-07-12:/preparing-your-heart-for-the-holy-spirit.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Claim Your Birthright - The Spirit-filled life is not optional or for a select few. When Christ died, this fullness became available to every believer. 2. Welcome Him as Friend, Not Foe -...&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Claim Your Birthright&lt;/strong&gt;  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Spirit-filled life is not optional or for a select few. When Christ died, this fullness became available to every believer.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Welcome Him as Friend, Not Foe&lt;/strong&gt;  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Holy Spirit isn’t strange or scary. He’s Jesus’ presence in you—gentle, loving, and good.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Surrender Everything&lt;/strong&gt;  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s not just about blessings. Are you ready to let go of your plans, pride, and control? True filling requires handing over every area of life.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Long for More Than Basics&lt;/strong&gt;  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Prayers, Bible study, and good deeds are vital—but they’re just the start. Crave deeper fellowship, purity, strength for service, and victory over temptation.  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Steps to Receive the Holy Spirit&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Offer Your Whole Self&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
   Present your body, thoughts, emotions, and will to God as an act of worship (Rom. 12:1–2).  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ask in Faith&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
   Simple, believing prayer is enough: “Ask, and it will be given you” (Luke 11:9–13).  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Live in Obedience&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
   The Spirit is promised to those who follow Christ’s commands (Acts 5:32).  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Trust His Promise&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
   Just as you received salvation by faith, receive the Spirit’s fullness the same way (Gal. 3:2).  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you believe it’s your right, yearn for His fullness, and take these steps with simple trust, the Holy Spirit will come and fill you. Tonight, as we sing “The Comforter Has Come,” open your heart, ask, and expect Him to move.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Books"></category><category term="Book-Summaries"></category><category term="Books"></category><category term="Chapter-Summaries"></category></entry><entry><title>The Promise of the Father: A Condensed Reflection</title><link href="https://preserving-holiness.github.io/the-promise-of-the-father.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2025-07-12T12:54:00-04:00</published><updated>2025-07-12T12:54:00-04:00</updated><author><name>A W Tozer and ChatGPT</name></author><id>tag:preserving-holiness.github.io,2025-07-12:/the-promise-of-the-father.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Opening Promise Jesus tells His disciples in Luke 24:49, "I send the promise of my Father upon you," pointing back to Joel's prophecy that God would pour out His Spirit on all people. Three Stages of the Promise 1. Promise Phase (John the Baptist to Resurrection) - Disciples knew Jesus...&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Opening Promise&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
Jesus tells His disciples in Luke 24:49, "I send the promise of my Father upon you," pointing back to Joel's prophecy that God would pour out His Spirit on all people.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Three Stages of the Promise&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
1. &lt;strong&gt;Promise Phase (John the Baptist to Resurrection)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
   - Disciples knew Jesus personally—His teachings, death, and resurrection.&lt;br&gt;
   - Jesus built their hope for a new power beyond what they already experienced.&lt;br&gt;
   - They expected an "outpouring" of divine energy they had not yet seen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Preparation Phase (Resurrection to Pentecost)&lt;/strong&gt;  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;After rising, Jesus commanded the disciples to "tarry" in Jerusalem.  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Their work paused so they could receive what had been promised.  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Though seemingly idle, they grew in unity and expectation, gathering 120 believers in prayer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Realization Phase (Pentecost)&lt;/strong&gt;  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The Holy Spirit arrived like a rushing wind and tongues of fire (Acts 2).  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Peter describes this as God "shedding forth" the Spirit—an overflow beyond their hopes.  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Believers gained new, inner proof of faith: the Spirit's direct witness in their hearts.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;External vs. Internal Evidence&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
- &lt;strong&gt;External Proofs&lt;/strong&gt;: Scriptures, John the Baptist’s testimony, God’s miracles, and Christ’s works all point to Jesus but rely on logic and outside signs.&lt;br&gt;
- &lt;strong&gt;Internal Witness&lt;/strong&gt;: Only the Holy Spirit gives an immediate, living assurance—like feeling alive—free from the need for argument.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Impact of the Holy Spirit&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
- &lt;strong&gt;Transformation&lt;/strong&gt;: Converts in distant lands, unfamiliar with Christian logic, believe and change by the Spirit’s power alone.&lt;br&gt;
- &lt;strong&gt;Emotion and Joy&lt;/strong&gt;: Early believers experienced vibrant emotion and spiritual delight, qualities lacking in many modern services.&lt;br&gt;
- &lt;strong&gt;Authority&lt;/strong&gt;: Freed from fear and doubt, they spoke with boldness rooted in life, not mere logic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ongoing Promise Today&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
Some claim the Spirit’s coming was a one-time event only for the first church. But if the fullness received by the apostles doesn’t apply to us, it’s like eating Peter’s meal in A.D. 33 and expecting it to nourish us now—impossible across centuries and seas.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Questions for Reflection&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
- Is the Father’s promise solely for first-century Christians, or must each believer be filled today?&lt;br&gt;
- Does "the new birth" and Spirit’s fullness happen once for all, or must we personally receive them?&lt;br&gt;
- Do we have what the early Church enjoyed, or have our expectations fallen short?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;A Call to Seek&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
Jesus urged His followers to wait because the Spirit’s coming would mean the difference between failure and success. The early Church said, "They were amazed," because God gave more than He promised.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Invitation&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
If today’s faith feels weaker than what was promised, admit the gap. Seek Scripture, prayer, obedience, and faith so that the Father’s promise may be yours in full—beyond expectation, just as in the first Pentecost.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Books"></category><category term="Book-Summaries"></category><category term="Books"></category><category term="Chapter-Summaries"></category></entry><entry><title>[Who Is the Holy Spirit?]</title><link href="https://preserving-holiness.github.io/who-is-the-holy-spirit.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2025-07-09T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2025-07-09T00:00:00-04:00</updated><author><name>A W Tozer and ChatGPT</name></author><id>tag:preserving-holiness.github.io,2025-07-09:/who-is-the-holy-spirit.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;--- &lt;strong&gt;Chapter 1: Who Is the Holy Spirit? (Abridged)&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;strong&gt;1. Defining “Spirit”&lt;/strong&gt; When we speak of spirit here, we aren’t talking about courage, temperament, or energy. Spirit is real—another mode of being, just as real as matter. While matter has weight, shape, and occupies space, spirit can penetrate everything—bodies, thoughts,...&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Chapter 1: Who Is the Holy Spirit? (Abridged)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;1. Defining “Spirit”&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
When we speak of spirit here, we aren’t talking about courage, temperament, or energy. Spirit is real—another mode of being, just as real as matter. While matter has weight, shape, and occupies space, spirit can penetrate everything—bodies, thoughts, even other spirit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2. What Is the Holy Spirit?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
The Holy Spirit is a divine Being existing in this same nonmaterial mode. No weight, size, or color—but no less real. He is not mere enthusiasm, genius, or inspiration. He is a Person: with will, intelligence, feeling, and the power to love, hear, and speak.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;3. Biblical and Historical Witness&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
- &lt;strong&gt;Creeds:&lt;/strong&gt; The Nicene Creed (AD 325) calls Him “Lord and Giver of life” to be worshiped with Father and Son. The Athanasian Creed repeats: “Such as the Father is, such is the Holy Ghost,” implying equality with the other Persons of the Trinity.
- &lt;strong&gt;Hymns:&lt;/strong&gt; Writers pray to the Holy Ghost with divine titles: “power divine,” “cleanse this guilty heart,” “reign supreme.” Such prayers can only be addressed to God.
- &lt;strong&gt;Scripture:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
  - &lt;strong&gt;Omnipresence:&lt;/strong&gt; “Whither shall I go from Your Spirit?” (Psalm 139:7) – only God is everywhere.&lt;br&gt;
  - &lt;strong&gt;Eternity:&lt;/strong&gt; Hebrews 9:14 speaks of the “eternal Spirit,” a quality no created being has.&lt;br&gt;
  - &lt;strong&gt;Baptismal Formula:&lt;/strong&gt; Matthew 28:19 instructs baptism “in the name of the Father, Son, and Holy Spirit,” placing the Spirit on equal footing with God.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;4. Why It Matters&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
Many Christians accept the doctrine of the Spirit without knowing or experiencing His power. Truths can lie dormant if we don’t teach and apply them. Just as belief in healing does little unless practiced, belief in the Spirit’s fullness does little unless we seek it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;5. What the Spirit Is Like&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
Everywhere, always present—He is indistinguishable in character from the Father and the Son. If Jesus walked among us today, we’d feel welcome, loved, safe. That is the Spirit: the same love, kindness, and warmth we find in Christ.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Invitation&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
Believe not just in doctrine but in living reality. Invite the Holy Spirit to fill your heart, transforming you from within with divine presence, power, and peace.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Books"></category><category term="Book-Summaries"></category><category term="Books"></category><category term="Chapter-Summaries"></category></entry><entry><title>Preface to How to be Filled with the Holy Spirit, by A. W. Tozer</title><link href="https://preserving-holiness.github.io/preface-to-how-to-be-filled-with-the-holy-spirit-by-a-w-tozer.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2025-07-05T18:58:00-04:00</published><updated>2025-07-05T18:58:00-04:00</updated><author><name>A. W. Tozer &amp; Gemini 2.5 Flash</name></author><id>tag:preserving-holiness.github.io,2025-07-05:/preface-to-how-to-be-filled-with-the-holy-spirit-by-a-w-tozer.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Preface to the Book.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Title: Preface to How to be Filled with the Holy Spirit, by A. W. Tozer
Date: 2025-07-05
Status: published
Category: Books
Tags: Books, Book-Summaries, Chapter-Summaries
Author: A. W. Tozer &amp;amp; Gemini 2.5 Flash
Summary: Preface to the Book.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Understanding the Holy Spirit&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This book, published by Moody Publishers, is a collection of sermons on the Holy Spirit.  Authored by A.W.T., it aims to guide believers towards a deeper understanding and relationship with the Holy Spirit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Key Features:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Content:&lt;/strong&gt; The book explores the identity of the Holy Spirit, the promise of the Father, how to be filled with the Holy Spirit, and how to cultivate a deeper companionship with Him.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Style:&lt;/strong&gt; Written in a conversational, informal style reflecting its origins as a series of sermons.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Purpose:&lt;/strong&gt; To help Christian believers develop a closer relationship with the Holy Spirit.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Copyright:&lt;/strong&gt; © 1952, 1992, 2001, 2016 by Moody Bible Institute of Chicago.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;ISBN:&lt;/strong&gt; 978-1-60066-799-2&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The proceeds from the book support Moody Bible Institute students.  The author notes that the book's informal style is a result of its sermon origins.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Books"></category><category term="Books"></category><category term="Book-Summaries"></category><category term="Chapter-Summaries"></category></entry></feed>