<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Preserving Holiness - Books</title><link href="https://preserving-holiness.github.io/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="https://preserving-holiness.github.io/feeds/books.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>https://preserving-holiness.github.io/</id><updated>2025-07-12T15:20:00-04:00</updated><entry><title>Conditions for Receiving Power</title><link href="https://preserving-holiness.github.io/conditions-for-receiving-power.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2025-07-12T15:20:00-04:00</published><updated>2025-07-12T15:20:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Asa Mahan and ChatGPT</name></author><id>tag:preserving-holiness.github.io,2025-07-12:/conditions-for-receiving-power.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Be Converted, Then Consecrated - Conversion means turning to Christ, leaving behind pride, selfishness, and doubt. It is a personal commitment for salvation. - Consecration is a deeper step: dedicating your life and abilities to Christ’s work—sharing the gospel and serving others. The first disciples were converted but waited...&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jesus promised his followers a special power: “Tarry in Jerusalem until you are clothed with power from on high” (Luke 24:49). This chapter explains how we can receive that power today.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;1. Be Converted, Then Consecrated&lt;/strong&gt;
- &lt;strong&gt;Conversion&lt;/strong&gt; means turning to Christ, leaving behind pride, selfishness, and doubt. It is a personal commitment for salvation.
- &lt;strong&gt;Consecration&lt;/strong&gt; is a deeper step: dedicating your life and abilities to Christ’s work—sharing the gospel and serving others. The first disciples were converted but waited to be consecrated before acting on their mission.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2. Accept the Commission&lt;/strong&gt;
- Jesus gave a clear mission: make disciples of all nations (Matthew 28:19–20). He then told them to wait for the promised power.
- True commitment means embracing this task as your life’s purpose. Every believer, not just pastors, is called to share Christ’s love in words and actions—through prayer, writing, work, or caring for others.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;3. Wait in Prayer and Faith&lt;/strong&gt;
- The disciples gathered in Jerusalem, prayed together, and asked God for strength each day. They did not simply pray once and go on with their business. They persisted until the Holy Spirit came at Pentecost (Acts 2).
- Genuine waiting involves active prayer, faith in Christ’s promise, and willingness to depend on God until he answers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;4. Four Key Needs&lt;/strong&gt;
Believers often miss out on this power because of four common obstacles:
  1. &lt;strong&gt;Unaware of the Commission:&lt;/strong&gt; Many Christians think only ministers share the gospel. Yet every follower of Christ is commissioned to be a witness.
  2. &lt;strong&gt;Doubtful of Power:&lt;/strong&gt; Some believe the Spirit’s special power is for a few gifted people. But Jesus promised it to all who believe.
  3. &lt;strong&gt;Weak Faith:&lt;/strong&gt; Without strong faith, we cannot claim Christ’s promise with confidence.
  4. &lt;strong&gt;Lack of Persistence:&lt;/strong&gt; We pray briefly and give up. Lasting prayer, like the disciples’, brings spiritual enduement.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;5. Assessing Church Weakness&lt;/strong&gt;
- Today, many ministries report minimal fruit. For example, mission boards often see only a few conversions per year per worker. This suggests a lack of sustained prayer and power-filled witness.
- Both church leaders and members share responsibility for this weakness. When the Church stays weak, ministry stays weak—and vice versa.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;6. Steps to Receive Power&lt;/strong&gt;
1. &lt;strong&gt;Review Your Salvation:&lt;/strong&gt; Ensure your personal faith in Christ is settled. Only then can you focus on others’ needs.
2. &lt;strong&gt;Embrace Your Calling:&lt;/strong&gt; Decide to spend your life in God’s service, however you are gifted.
3. &lt;strong&gt;Pray Earnestly:&lt;/strong&gt; Gather with other believers, pray regularly, and hold fast to God’s promise.
4. &lt;strong&gt;Wait in Faith:&lt;/strong&gt; Do not stop praying until you sense the Spirit’s empowering presence.
5. &lt;strong&gt;Step Out Boldly:&lt;/strong&gt; When you receive power, act on God’s call—preach, serve, and live as Christ’s witness.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Conclusion&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
The promise of power is for every Christian. Like the first disciples, we must be converted, consecrated, and persistent in prayer. Then, God will clothe us with the Spirit’s power to fulfill our mission and bring many to Christ.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Books"></category><category term="Book-Summaries"></category><category term="Books"></category><category term="Chapter-Summaries"></category></entry><entry><title>Who May Expect the Enduement of Power?</title><link href="https://preserving-holiness.github.io/who-may-expect-the-enduement-of-power.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2025-07-12T15:18:00-04:00</published><updated>2025-07-12T15:18:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Asa Mahan and ChatGPT</name></author><id>tag:preserving-holiness.github.io,2025-07-12:/who-may-expect-the-enduement-of-power.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;In John 14:15–17, Jesus promises to send the Holy Spirit—the “Comforter” or Spirit of truth—to abide with believers forever. Christians across history have witnessed this divine power in every form of ministry, from private conversation to public preaching. While some individuals experience it more strongly than others, the gift itself...&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In John 14:15–17, Jesus promises to send the Holy Spirit—the “Comforter” or Spirit of truth—to abide with believers forever. Christians across history have witnessed this divine power in every form of ministry, from private conversation to public preaching. While some individuals experience it more strongly than others, the gift itself belongs to every Christian called to share the gospel.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Universal Promise to the Church&lt;/strong&gt;  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The command to make disciples of all nations was given to the entire Church, not only the apostles. Accordingly, the promise of a divine enduement of power applies to all who labor in Christ’s name, wherever the duty to win souls exists.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Not Limited by Office, Gender, Age, or Education&lt;/strong&gt;  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Laymen and Clergy:&lt;/strong&gt; From Stephen to Father Carpenter (a self-taught lay evangelist whose labors led to thousands of conversions), both ordained ministers and laypeople have received this gift in remarkable measure.  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Women:&lt;/strong&gt; The New Testament records female coworkers in the gospel, and history abounds with women whose anointed words stirred revivals. Churches and mission boards are increasingly recognizing their God‑given effectiveness.  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Young and Old:&lt;/strong&gt; Some receive this power immediately upon conversion; others grow into it over years. It rests on both new converts and veteran Christians alike.  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Cultured and Unlearned:&lt;/strong&gt; Human eloquence and scholarship cannot substitute for the Spirit’s power. Even the fisherman Peter preached with transformative effect after his baptism of fire at Pentecost.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Conditions and Characteristics of the Enduement&lt;/strong&gt;  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;A Gift, Not a Skill:&lt;/strong&gt; It is an instantaneous anointing—a gift of the Spirit—rather than the fruit of training or habit. Its depth may grow or wane depending on faithful use.  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Essential for Conversion:&lt;/strong&gt; No measure of human persuasion can truly convert without the Spirit impressing God’s truth on the heart.  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Vulnerability:&lt;/strong&gt; The gift can be quenched by spiritual neglect or disobedience, underscoring the need for continual dependence on God.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Implications for the Church&lt;/strong&gt;  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Seminaries and Leadership:&lt;/strong&gt; Academic credentials must not eclipse the evidence of Spirit‑empowered ministry. Those who teach future ministers should themselves display and affirm the indispensability of this power.  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Church Offices:&lt;/strong&gt; Pastors, elders, deacons, missionaries, and other leaders ought to exhibit and encourage this enduement. A congregation without Spirit‑filled laborers reflects either a pastor who lacks this fire or one who fails to nurture it among members.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Conclusion&lt;/strong&gt;: The promise of power from on high is coextensive with the call to witness. All Christians—regardless of station, gender, or education—may and should ask for this anointing to win souls for Christ. Without it, all human efforts are ineffectual; with it, even the humblest believer becomes a compelling instrument of God’s saving grace.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Books"></category><category term="Book-Summaries"></category><category term="Books"></category><category term="Chapter-Summaries"></category></entry><entry><title>An Exhibition of the Power from on High</title><link href="https://preserving-holiness.github.io/an-exhibition-of-the-power-from-on-high.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2025-07-12T15:16:00-04:00</published><updated>2025-07-12T15:16:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Asa Mahan and ChatGPT</name></author><id>tag:preserving-holiness.github.io,2025-07-12:/an-exhibition-of-the-power-from-on-high.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Preparatory Agony and Divine Encouragement Fearful of hostile reactions, Finney was encouraged by the Lord through Acts 18:9–10 (“Be not afraid… for I have much people in this city”). Overwhelmed with compassion, he spent Saturday in fervent prayer, wrestling with tears in a nearby grove. Each return to the grove...&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this chapter, Charles Finney recounts his early experience preaching in a remote part of Jefferson County, New York, after being invited by a Female Missionary Society. Arriving in Antwerp in early May, he found no active church life—the meetinghouse was closed and the townspeople were steeped in profanity, which distressed him deeply.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Preparatory Agony and Divine Encouragement&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
Fearful of hostile reactions, Finney was encouraged by the Lord through Acts 18:9–10 (“Be not afraid… for I have much people in this city”). Overwhelmed with compassion, he spent Saturday in fervent prayer, wrestling with tears in a nearby grove. Each return to the grove brought relief only when it was time for the Sunday service.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;First Sermon and Revival’s Spark&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
On Sunday morning, Finney preached from John 3:16, contrasting God’s love with humanity’s contempt. Directly addressing known profaners in the audience—pointing out those he had overheard cursing—his honest rebuke melted the hearts of listeners rather than alienating them. The church caretaker, moved by the morning meeting, reopened the brick meetinghouse for an afternoon service, which was likewise filled and powerfully impacted. A revival ignited in Antwerp and spread rapidly throughout the countryside.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journey to “Sodom” and a Second Outpouring&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
Two weeks later, asked to preach in a hostile neighborhood mockingly called “Sodom,” Finney walked there on a sweltering Monday, nearly faint and discouraged. Upon arrival, the discordant singing tormented him until he fell to his knees in desperate prayer. God answered with a vivid text: “Up, get you out of this place… for the Lord will destroy this city.” He expounded on the destruction of Sodom, Abraham’s intercession, and Lot’s lonely faith, which initially angered the congregation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As he pressed the message home, God’s presence struck the assembly suddenly and overwhelmingly: men, women, and children collapsed under conviction, crying out for mercy. Finney knelt beside individuals, whispering the gospel until they grasped Christ, then lifted their own prayers for others. The meeting lasted until sunset, after which Finney left the old man known as “Lot” to continue.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Lingering Impact&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
The following day, many remained under deep conviction in a private home. Finney preached again, and all found relief and hope. Years later he learned that his converts in “Sodom” remained committed believers, and one young man, converted at that first meeting, went on to pastoral leadership. This outpouring, Finney concludes, produced permanent fruit throughout that region.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Books"></category><category term="Book-Summaries"></category><category term="Books"></category><category term="Chapter-Summaries"></category></entry><entry><title>The Enduement of Power</title><link href="https://preserving-holiness.github.io/the-enduement-of-power.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2025-07-12T15:14:00-04:00</published><updated>2025-07-12T15:14:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Asa Mahan and ChatGPT</name></author><id>tag:preserving-holiness.github.io,2025-07-12:/the-enduement-of-power.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;How to Receive 1. Consecration. The early disciples devoted themselves wholly to Christ’s mission. 2. Prayer and Waiting. They prayed together and waited in Jerusalem until Pentecost, when the Holy Spirit fell (Luke 11:13). These steps remain both the...&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;How to Receive&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
1. &lt;strong&gt;Consecration.&lt;/strong&gt; The early disciples devoted themselves wholly to Christ’s mission.&lt;br&gt;
2. &lt;strong&gt;Prayer and Waiting.&lt;/strong&gt; They prayed together and waited in Jerusalem until Pentecost, when the Holy Spirit fell (Luke 11:13).  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These steps remain both the promise and the pattern for all ages: surrender everything, pray persistently, and trust God to pour out His Spirit.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Barriers to Power&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
Though everyone prays for this gift, many remain powerless. Finney identifies key hindrances—sins and attitudes that keep the Spirit from coming in fullness:**  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Unwillingness or Half‑heartedness.&lt;/strong&gt; Not truly wanting God’s will enough to give up comfort or control.  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Unconfessed Sin.&lt;/strong&gt; Self‑indulgence, dishonesty, resentment, and unforgiveness block God’s ear.  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Self‑Reliance.&lt;/strong&gt; Depending on intellect, training, or denominational ties rather than the Spirit’s work.  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Resistance to the Spirit.&lt;/strong&gt; Ignoring conviction, quenching zeal, grumbling, and allowing evil tempers.  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Neglect and Imbalance.&lt;/strong&gt; Over‑busyness, lack of prayer, careless study, and impatience.  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Worldliness and Selfish Ambition.&lt;/strong&gt; Pursuing personal gain, status, or denominational advantage.  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Unbelief.&lt;/strong&gt; The worst of all—doubting God’s promise makes Him out to be a liar.  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Until these are dealt with, asking in prayer cannot secure the promised power.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Peace vs. Power&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
Many Christians enjoy forgiveness (the Spirit’s peace) but stop short of seeking anointing for service (the Spirit’s power). True empowerment comes only when believers go beyond conversion to full dependence on the Holy Spirit.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Conclusion&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
If we lay everything on God’s altar—time, talents, tithes—and test His promise, He will open the windows of heaven and pour out a blessing until there is no more room to receive it.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Books"></category><category term="Book-Summaries"></category><category term="Books"></category><category term="Chapter-Summaries"></category></entry><entry><title>The Consolation of the Spirit</title><link href="https://preserving-holiness.github.io/the-consolation-of-the-spirit.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2025-07-12T15:13:00-04:00</published><updated>2025-07-12T15:13:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Asa Mahan and ChatGPT</name></author><id>tag:preserving-holiness.github.io,2025-07-12:/the-consolation-of-the-spirit.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;In Chapter 12, the author explains how God uses hard times (“afflictive providences”) to purify and strengthen believers, comparing our trials to refining precious metals in a furnace. The Furnace of Affliction - Just as only intense heat can purify silver and gold, God allows serious trials to develop our...&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In Chapter 12, the author explains how God uses hard times (“afflictive providences”) to purify and strengthen believers, comparing our trials to refining precious metals in a furnace.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;The Furnace of Affliction&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Just as only intense heat can purify silver and gold, God allows serious trials to develop our most valuable virtues.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Easy challenges may form some good habits, but deep, lasting qualities bloom only under severe testing.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Responding to Trials&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Afflictions often strike unexpectedly, testing our faith and hope.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Believers must hear God’s voice calling them to trust and obey, even when pain or loss seems pointless.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Patient endurance—"holding fast"—secures the "crown of life." Failing to trust costs our reward.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Nine Benefits of Afflictive Providences&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Awakening Eternal Realities&lt;/strong&gt;: Suffering shifts our focus from worldly comfort to God, duty, and eternity—truths we might ignore in prosperity.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Submitting to God’s Will&lt;/strong&gt;: Deep trials teach our wills to align fully with God’s, bringing lasting peace and contentment.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Strengthening Faith and Hope&lt;/strong&gt;: When our own strength fails, we learn to lean on God’s limitless power, making trust a habit.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Assurance of Salvation&lt;/strong&gt;: Obedience in hardship brings a clear sense of being accepted by God and confident hope.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Visions of Glory&lt;/strong&gt;: Only through hardship can we truly appreciate promises of future glory and find joy in them.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Christ’s Presence in Suffering&lt;/strong&gt;: Afflictions draw us closer to Christ’s own sufferings, making our trials feel like a shared fellowship with Him.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Developing Divine Traits&lt;/strong&gt;: Trials refine qualities like humility, empathy for others, steadfast love, and devotion to Christ.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Understanding Sorrow&lt;/strong&gt;: Experiencing suffering teaches us what sorrow means—and can even make it beautiful when seen as part of God’s plan.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Empowering Others&lt;/strong&gt;: Those who endure hardship can comfort and guide others by the same comfort they received from God.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;When Is a Trial Complete?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Patience is "perfect" when we fully accept God’s plan without wishing to change our allotted trials or comforts.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A truly sanctified mind views trials as "clouds of glory"—bearing the shadow of God’s protection and pierced by His light.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;The Apostle Paul’s Example&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Despite countless sufferings—imprisonment, beatings, shipwrecks—Paul radiated joy and contentment.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;He testified that in weakness he found strength through Christ, learning to be content in any situation.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Paul embraced persecution for Christ’s sake and lived by faith, showing that believers today can do the same.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Afflictions are not senseless pains but God’s chosen means to refine and equip us for eternal joy.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;When we trust and obey during hardship, we discover God’s presence, power, and promises in a deeper way.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Embracing suffering as the "Cross of Christ" leads to everlasting life and transforms sorrow into hope and praise.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><category term="Books"></category><category term="Book-Summaries"></category><category term="Books"></category><category term="Chapter-Summaries"></category></entry><entry><title>The Fountain Opened for Sin and Uncleanness</title><link href="https://preserving-holiness.github.io/the-fountain-opened-for-sin-and-uncleanness.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2025-07-12T15:12:00-04:00</published><updated>2025-07-12T15:12:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Asa Mahan and ChatGPT</name></author><id>tag:preserving-holiness.github.io,2025-07-12:/the-fountain-opened-for-sin-and-uncleanness.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Ancient Fountains as a Spiritual Picture In ancient Palestine, cities dug deep rock reservoirs and sealed them to store water against droughts or sieges. When opened, these fountains gave life—cool drinking water and a means to cleanse. If the reservoir cracked and ran dry, it was called a “broken...&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Key Texts:&lt;/strong&gt;
- 1 Corinthians 1:30; Zechariah 13:1; Titus 3:5&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;1. Ancient Fountains as a Spiritual Picture&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In ancient Palestine, cities dug deep rock reservoirs and sealed them to store water against droughts or sieges. When opened, these fountains gave life—cool drinking water and a means to cleanse. If the reservoir cracked and ran dry, it was called a “broken cistern” and was a source of despair.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In Scripture, God and Christ are often compared to these fountains:
- &lt;strong&gt;Fountain sealed:&lt;/strong&gt; A special source of joy guarded for someone beloved.
- &lt;strong&gt;Fountain opened:&lt;/strong&gt; A time of deliverance when water (life) flows freely.
- &lt;strong&gt;Broken cistern:&lt;/strong&gt; False hopes that disappoint.
- &lt;strong&gt;Fountain of living water:&lt;/strong&gt; God’s continual supply of spiritual life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;2. Salvation in Christ: Objective and Subjective&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Objective:&lt;/strong&gt; Christ’s redemption is perfect and complete, offering everything our souls need. It stands ready whether people accept it or not.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Subjective:&lt;/strong&gt; It becomes real when the soul desperately seeks freedom from sin, recognizes Christ’s sacrifice, and trusts in His cleansing power—like city-dwellers urgently praying to open their sealed reservoir.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Closed fountain (to the unbelieving soul):&lt;/strong&gt; Christ’s grace is ignored when hearts cling to worldly pleasures, pride, or self-righteousness.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Opened fountain (to the believer):&lt;/strong&gt; When the Holy Spirit opens hearts, Christ becomes “the power and wisdom of God” for redemption, offering peace and strength.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;3. A Higher Blessing: Baptism of the Holy Spirit&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Beyond initial salvation, believers can experience a deeper blessing when filled with the Holy Spirit (the Pentecost event). Before this:
- Faith is cautious and dim.
- Assurance is weak; obedience is by effort.
- Joy and peace come in small measures.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After the Spirit’s outpouring:
- Truth shines clearly; doubts vanish.
- Strength flows naturally; obedience becomes joyful.
- Inner thirst for God is fully quenched--"living water springs up into everlasting life."&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;4. Prophetic Promise: "In That Day"&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Zechariah’s prophecy speaks of a future time when every believer will experience this Spirit-filled life:
- God will purify His people completely—no sin found (Jer. 31:33–34; Ezek. 36:25).
- The Spirit will be poured out on all believers, young and old (Joel 2:28–29).
- The Church will shine so brightly that nations will come to its light (Isa. 60:1–3).
- This marks the beginning of lasting glory and the millennium.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;5. Conditions for the Fountain to Flow&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;For Individuals:&lt;/strong&gt;
1. Deep hunger and thirst for holiness.
2. Prayerful seeking of divine fullness.
3. Open faith that Christ alone meets every need.
4. A personal encounter where the Spirit reveals Christ’s fullness.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once one believer is filled, their testimony stirs others to seek the same. Their transformed lives become rivers of life reaching many.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;For Churches:&lt;/strong&gt;
1. Hold and preach the truth of full redemption.
2. Live out its cleansing power in members’ lives.
3. Manifest the Spirit’s transforming work visibly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A church meeting these conditions shines as a beacon; around it, people find Christ and cleansing as from an opened fountain.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;6. The Role of Methodism&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Methodism’s creed centers on full and free redemption in Christ. Its glory lies in:
- Upholding this gospel truth.
- Demonstrating its life-changing power in believers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If Methodism remains true, it will lead many into the Spirit’s fullness. If it falls into dead orthodoxy, it will lose its mission and shame itself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This abridgment preserves the core imagery and teaching: Christ as a sealed fountain opened to cleanse and empower believers, culminating in a universal outpouring of the Spirit that fulfills prophecy and marks the Church’s greatest glory.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Books"></category><category term="Book-Summaries"></category><category term="Books"></category><category term="Chapter-Summaries"></category></entry><entry><title>Witness, Demonstration, and Power of the Spirit</title><link href="https://preserving-holiness.github.io/witness-demonstration-and-power-of-the-spirit.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2025-07-12T15:11:00-04:00</published><updated>2025-07-12T15:11:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Asa Mahan and ChatGPT</name></author><id>tag:preserving-holiness.github.io,2025-07-12:/witness-demonstration-and-power-of-the-spirit.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;This chapter explores how the Holy Spirit illuminates the mind, bears witness to divine truth, and empowers believers. Using New Testament texts—such as Acts 10:38, 1 John 5:6, Romans 8:16, and 1 Corinthians 2:4—the author shows that the Spirit produces deep, certain, and life-giving conviction. Forms of Spiritual Knowledge 1....&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This chapter explores how the Holy Spirit illuminates the mind, bears witness to divine truth, and empowers believers. Using New Testament texts—such as Acts 10:38, 1 John 5:6, Romans 8:16, and 1 Corinthians 2:4—the author shows that the Spirit produces deep, certain, and life-giving conviction.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Forms of Spiritual Knowledge&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
1. &lt;strong&gt;Opinion vs. Certainty&lt;/strong&gt;: Belief and doubt occupy outer circles of thought. When a truth moves from doubt into conviction, it becomes a matter of absolute certainty—a form of knowledge proper.&lt;br&gt;
2. &lt;strong&gt;Intuitive and Demonstrative Knowledge&lt;/strong&gt;: Intuitive knowledge (self-awareness) and demonstrative knowledge (logical proof) both pale next to spiritual illumination, which yields direct, doubt-free, inward knowing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Evidence of Divine Illumination&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
- Truth once remote can suddenly shine with vivid clarity, making past doubts seem absurd.&lt;br&gt;
- Suffering saints, on their deathbeds, have experienced the Spirit’s illumination, transforming fear into joy and anticipation.&lt;br&gt;
- Skeptics and moralists also report dramatic conversions when confronted by the Spirit: prophetic accuracy of Scripture, moral self-examination, and sudden insight into personal sin leave no room for skepticism.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Spirit’s Witness to the Bible&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
- The Spirit inspired Scripture and confirms its truth through fulfilled prophecy, miracles, and the Bible’s unique divine signature.&lt;br&gt;
- Personal experiences—answered prayer, inner transformation, and moral renewal—act as inner proofs that the Spirit is truth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Witness of Adoption&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
- The Spirit not only teaches truth but also confirms believers’ status as God’s children (Romans 8:15–16). Through feelings of filial comfort, peace amid trial, and bold prayer, we sense God’s fatherly care.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Fellowship and Empowerment&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
- Believers often oscillate between doubt and assurance until, by the Spirit’s power, they enter a state of clear vision and unshakable faith.&lt;br&gt;
- Scriptural promises of divine love and care become personally real, producing joy, courage, and an empowered life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Conditions for Full Spiritual Power&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
1. &lt;strong&gt;Self-Emptying&lt;/strong&gt;: Recognize personal weakness and renounce self-reliance.&lt;br&gt;
2. &lt;strong&gt;Dependent Confidence&lt;/strong&gt;: Trust fully in God’s sufficiency and the Spirit’s power.&lt;br&gt;
3. &lt;strong&gt;Perseverance&lt;/strong&gt;: Maintain confidence in grace, watch for complacency, and remain spiritually vigilant.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When these conditions are met, the church and individual believers can experience sustained victories, abundant fruit, and an ever-deepening fellowship with Christ. Without them, faith remains intermittent—marked by doubt, struggle, and spiritual dryness.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Conclusion&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
The Spirit is central to Christian faith: He enlightens, convinces, adopts, and empowers. By yielding to Him—abandoning self-effort, embracing God’s strength, and persevering in faith—believers can move from doubt-filled shadows into the light of full assurance, experiencing all the "exceeding greatness of His power to us-ward" (Ephesians 1:19). This power is not reserved for a spiritual elite but is available to every believer who walks by the Spirit, offering victory, transformation, and the joy of divine fellowship.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Books"></category><category term="Book-Summaries"></category><category term="Books"></category><category term="Chapter-Summaries"></category></entry><entry><title>The Unity of the Spirit</title><link href="https://preserving-holiness.github.io/the-unity-of-the-spirit.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2025-07-12T15:09:00-04:00</published><updated>2025-07-12T15:09:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Asa Mahan and ChatGPT</name></author><id>tag:preserving-holiness.github.io,2025-07-12:/the-unity-of-the-spirit.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;“Endeavouring to keep the unity of the Spirit in the bond of peace.” (Ephesians 4:3) “I in them, and Thou in Me, that they may be made perfect in one.” (John 17:23) 1. What Is the “Unity of the Spirit”? This term describes the deep oneness the Holy Spirit creates...&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Key Texts:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;“Endeavouring to keep the unity of the Spirit in the bond of peace.” (Ephesians 4:3)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;“I in them, and Thou in Me, that they may be made perfect in one.” (John 17:23)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;1. What Is the “Unity of the Spirit”?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This term describes the deep oneness the Holy Spirit creates among believers whose hearts He fills. It isn’t uniformity in every minor detail, but a shared likeness to Christ in essential matters. Just as every star differs yet shines by the same light, each Christian retains unique gifts and opinions on non-essentials while reflecting Christ’s character.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Core features include:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Christ-likeness in character:&lt;/strong&gt; Meekness, gentleness, love of truth, purity, patient endurance, and unconditional obedience mirror Jesus in each believer.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Supreme affection for Christ:&lt;/strong&gt; All believers center their hopes, joys, and actions on Christ, forsaking worldly ties and “sect” labels.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Fellowship with Father and Son:&lt;/strong&gt; Every Christian shares the inward life of the Trinity—“Christ in you, the hope of glory”—binding hearts in identical spiritual experience.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Impartial love for Christ in others:&lt;/strong&gt; True unity esteems Christ’s image and holiness wherever it appears, forging brotherly love that transcends personal differences.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;2. Why a “Bond of Peace”?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A bond of peace goes beyond mere absence of conflict. It resists any force—wrong opinions, slander, distance—that might divide. Like David and Jonathan’s unbreakable friendship, Christian unity endures trials because it rests on shared life in Christ, not on fleeting affinities or agreements. If discord arises, repentant hearts can forgive and reunite, often more tightly than before.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;3. The Call to Keep This Unity&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Paul’s appeal (“endeavouring to keep the unity of the Spirit in the bond of peace”) implies two things:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Active effort:&lt;/strong&gt; This unity won’t preserve itself; it demands watchful prayer, humility, and love.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ongoing vigilance:&lt;/strong&gt; Even genuine fellowship can be tarnished by misunderstanding or sin, so we must guard against division.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;4. Reasons for Our Endeavor&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;It’s the highest state of Christian living.&lt;/strong&gt;
   Walking in shared light and love with God and one another is the pinnacle of spiritual blessing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Christ’s own emphasis.&lt;/strong&gt;
   He prayed that all believers “may be one … that the world may believe” (John 17:21). Unity in love is the church’s hallmark before the world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;God’s example of sacrificial love.&lt;/strong&gt;
   As Christ laid down His life for us, so we are called to live and, if needed, suffer for our brothers and sisters.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Danger of neglect.&lt;/strong&gt;
   Without prayerful effort, “that old serpent” will sow discord, eroding the simplicity and power of our shared faith.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Proof of genuine faith.&lt;/strong&gt;
   Love for fellow believers is the clearest evidence of new life in Christ. To hate a brother is to forfeit fellowship with God.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;5. True Christian Fellowship Defined&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Not mere polite association&lt;/strong&gt;, but a bond grounded in mutual oneness with Christ.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;No tolerance for unrepentant sin&lt;/strong&gt; within the body; discipline protects the unity.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Open welcome to those who show true evidence of fellowship with Father and Son&lt;/strong&gt;, regardless of non-essential differences.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Conclusion&lt;/strong&gt;
“Unity of the Spirit in the bond of peace” is both a gift of the Holy Spirit and a daily task for every Christian. It means living out our shared identity in Christ—loving Him supremely, loving one another authentically, and guarding against all that would divide us. In so doing, we display the beauty of the gospel and fulfill Christ’s deepest desire: that His followers be perfectly one, just as He and the Father are one.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Books"></category><category term="Book-Summaries"></category><category term="Books"></category><category term="Chapter-Summaries"></category></entry><entry><title>The Fellowship of the Spirit</title><link href="https://preserving-holiness.github.io/the-fellowship-of-the-spirit.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2025-07-12T15:08:00-04:00</published><updated>2025-07-12T15:08:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Asa Mahan and ChatGPT</name></author><id>tag:preserving-holiness.github.io,2025-07-12:/the-fellowship-of-the-spirit.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The Meaning of Fellowship - Fellowship is more than companionship or working together. It means an intimate sharing of mind, heart, and purpose. - True fellowship requires a shared understanding, common interests, and mutual affection that blends thoughts and feelings into one harmonious relationship. - Our deepest human joy...&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Key Scripture:&lt;/strong&gt; "And truly our fellowship is with the Father, and with His Son Jesus Christ." (1 John 1:3)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;1. The Meaning of Fellowship&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Fellowship is more than companionship or working together. It means an intimate sharing of mind, heart, and purpose.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;True fellowship requires a shared understanding, common interests, and mutual affection that blends thoughts and feelings into one harmonious relationship.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Our deepest human joy comes when minds connect in this way—sharing joys, easing sorrows, and growing together.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2. Fellowship with God&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Sin broke our perfect friendship with God. Redemption restores us to fellowship with the Father and with His Son, Jesus Christ.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;This divine fellowship is a growing, lifelong relationship in which we progressively share God’s character, love, and purposes.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Though God’s infinity could overwhelm us, the Spirit brings fellowship in stages we can bear, revealing more of God as we grow in faith and love.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;3. The Spirit’s Work&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The Holy Spirit unites our hearts to God, showing us Christ’s love and the Father’s heart toward us.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Rather than dwelling on the Spirit Himself, we experience the Spirit by knowing Christ in us and the Father’s presence around us.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Eternal life is knowing the Father and Jesus Christ intimately, through the Spirit’s power in us.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;4. Signs of Divine Fellowship&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Intimate prayer&lt;/em&gt;: Talking to God as a close friend, confident of His attentive love.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Inner transformation&lt;/em&gt;: Being changed from glory to glory—our character reflecting Christ’s humility, love, and patience.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Comfort in trials&lt;/em&gt;: Finding peace and strength in suffering, knowing Christ sympathizes with and sustains us.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Joy and peace&lt;/em&gt;: Experiencing "joy unspeakable" and "the peace of God, which passes all understanding."&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Empowered living&lt;/em&gt;: Strength to serve, pray boldly, and walk in holiness through the Spirit’s power.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;5. Fellowship with One Another&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;1 John 1:7 reminds us that as we walk in God’s light, we share true fellowship with other believers.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Superficial religion cannot produce deep friendship—only hearts purified by the Spirit can truly rejoice and empathize together.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In Spirit-filled communities, we reflect Christ’s image to one another and share rich inner life in God.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;6. Barriers to Fellowship&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Unbelief, fear, and secret sin hinder intimacy with God and with others.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If God seems distant in prayer, self-examination and repentance open the way back to His presence.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;7. The Path Forward&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The goal: full fellowship with the Father and the Son—walking "in the light, as He is in the light," in perfect love and joy.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The key step: receive and rely on the Spirit’s anointing—trusting God’s love, seeking purification, and obeying His Word.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Progress is not by human effort alone but by trusting God’s promise to dwell in us and transform us from within.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Conclusion&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;True Christian maturity is fellowship—a mutual indwelling between our spirits and God’s. As we open our hearts, the Spirit brings us into deeper communion with the Father and the Son, shaping us more into Christ’s likeness and filling us with joy, peace, and love. Our part is simply to believe His love, walk in the light, and rejoice in the fellowship He provides.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Books"></category><category term="Book-Summaries"></category><category term="Books"></category><category term="Chapter-Summaries"></category></entry><entry><title>Guidance for Seeking the Holy Spirit’s Baptism</title><link href="https://preserving-holiness.github.io/guidance-for-seeking-the-holy-spirits-baptism.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2025-07-12T15:07:00-04:00</published><updated>2025-07-12T15:07:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Asa Mahan and ChatGPT</name></author><id>tag:preserving-holiness.github.io,2025-07-12:/guidance-for-seeking-the-holy-spirits-baptism.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Scripture Foundations - Acts 15:8–9 and Ephesians 4:30 remind us God purifies hearts by faith and seals us with the Spirit. 1. Avoid Preconceptions - Don’t worry about how or when you will receive the Spirit. Jesus promised power but did not explain the details to His disciples. - Instead...&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Scripture Foundations&lt;/strong&gt;
- Acts 15:8–9 and Ephesians 4:30 remind us God purifies hearts by faith and seals us with the Spirit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;1. Avoid Preconceptions&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Don’t worry about how or when you will receive the Spirit. Jesus promised power but did not explain the details to His disciples.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Instead of guessing what you will feel, focus on prayer and Scripture. When the Spirit comes, you will recognize new joy, clearer understanding, and deeper fellowship with God.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;2. Accept Inner Struggles&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;During preparation, you may uncover hidden faults. This is normal and means God is cleaning your heart.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Think of it like a deep house cleaning: it looks messy before it becomes spotless.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Keep repenting, dedicating yourself to Christ, and praying until your heart is a temple for the Holy Spirit.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;3. Be Patient in the Process&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The apostles waited over forty days for the Spirit. You may wait even longer. Don’t give up.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;God tests your faith and perseverance to strengthen you. Stay humble and persistent in prayer.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Counsels and Admonitions&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Believe in the Promise&lt;/strong&gt;  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;First, decide if God has truly promised to send the Holy Spirit after faith in Christ.  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you doubt, study the Scriptures until you’re convinced. Then claim that promise confidently in prayer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Keep Assurance of Sonship&lt;/strong&gt;  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When you repent and accept Christ, you are a child of God. Never doubt your acceptance as long as you don’t take it back.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Hold Fast to the Promise&lt;/strong&gt;  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Treat the Spirit’s gift as absolutely yours by faith in Christ. This firm belief helps you persevere in seeking the Spirit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Continue Seeking&lt;/strong&gt;  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Remain dedicated—pray, search, wait—and God will "do above all you ask or think" (Ephesians 3:20).  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The Spirit’s Discipline&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Receiving the Spirit begins a lifelong journey. God may lead you through trials to shape virtues like patience and endurance.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Great comfort often follows great sorrow, and victory follows conflict with temptation.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Paul’s "thorn in the flesh" taught him humility and gave him insight to comfort others.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Every challenge you endure refines your character and expands your ability to serve.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Key Points&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Trials build strength:&lt;/strong&gt; Hardships cultivate patience and faith.  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Service grows through suffering:&lt;/strong&gt; Trials prepare you to help others.  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Steady light:&lt;/strong&gt; Despite ups and downs, the Spirit’s seal ensures ongoing peace, sonship, and joy.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Temptations and Errors in the Higher Life&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Spiritual Pride&lt;/strong&gt;  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Avoid talking about yourself to glorify self. Instead, share what Christ has done for you to glorify Him.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Presumption&lt;/strong&gt;  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Don’t rely on your own strength alone. Continue in watchfulness, prayer, and the armor of God.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Neglecting Learning&lt;/strong&gt;  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Spirit doesn’t replace study. You need both divine guidance and disciplined learning to grow.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Refusing to Confess&lt;/strong&gt;  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Even filled with the Spirit, you can sin. Confess quickly and humbly to restore joy and fellowship.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Remember:&lt;/strong&gt; The Spirit equips you, but you must walk humbly, study diligently, and confess promptly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If you haven’t yet received the Holy Spirit since believing, you are missing a vital promise.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If you know the promise but don’t seek it, you risk losing your birthright of deeper joy and power.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Commit now: watch, wait, and pray until Christ sends the Spirit.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Then you will understand God’s love fully, rejoice always, pray continually, and be kept blameless until Christ returns (1 Thessalonians 5:16–23).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><category term="Books"></category></entry><entry><title>Preparation for the Baptisms of the Spirit (Condensed)</title><link href="https://preserving-holiness.github.io/preparation-for-the-baptisms-of-the-spirit-condensed.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2025-07-12T15:04:00-04:00</published><updated>2025-07-12T15:04:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Asa Mahan and ChatGPT</name></author><id>tag:preserving-holiness.github.io,2025-07-12:/preparation-for-the-baptisms-of-the-spirit-condensed.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Key Scripture Foundations - Jesus promised the Holy Spirit would come after His departure to empower believers (John 16:7–8; Luke 11:13). - His post‑resurrection act of breathing on the disciples (John 20:22) and the instruction to wait in Jerusalem (Acts 1:4–8) served to cultivate the expectant, unified mindset needed for...&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Key Scripture Foundations&lt;/strong&gt;
- Jesus promised the Holy Spirit would come after His departure to empower believers (John 16:7–8; Luke 11:13).
- His post‑resurrection act of breathing on the disciples (John 20:22) and the instruction to wait in Jerusalem (Acts 1:4–8) served to cultivate the expectant, unified mindset needed for Pentecost.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Purpose of Rituals and Ordinances&lt;/strong&gt;
- Ceremonies like laying on of hands accompanied baptism, Communion, and prayer but had no inherent power; their effectiveness relied on the recipient’s spiritual readiness.
- Early formalism arose when the Church valued outward rites over inward preparation. True baptism of the Spirit requires both faith in God’s promises and a heart tuned by earnest seeking.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Essential Heart Preparation&lt;/strong&gt;
1. &lt;strong&gt;Deep Awareness of Need:&lt;/strong&gt; Every recipient first recognizes a soul‑aching void that only Christ can fill.
2. &lt;strong&gt;Faith in Christ’s Fullness:&lt;/strong&gt; Conviction that through faith and prayer God will supply that need.
3. &lt;strong&gt;Intense Desire and Purpose:&lt;/strong&gt; A fixed resolve to seek, pray, and wait until the Spirit comes.
4. &lt;strong&gt;Waiting Expectation:&lt;/strong&gt; Patient yet fervent expectancy, sustained until the blessing arrives.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Illustrative Examples&lt;/strong&gt;
- &lt;strong&gt;Cornelius (Acts 10):&lt;/strong&gt; His fasting and praying in Joppa created the receptivity that led to the Spirit’s outpouring while hearing Peter.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Moses (Exodus 33–34):&lt;/strong&gt; After the golden calf incident, Moses’ dependence on God’s presence and his request “show me Thy glory” were met with divine promises and instructions that heightened his expectancy until God manifested Himself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Elisha (2 Kings 2):&lt;/strong&gt; Determined not to lose Elijah before receiving a “double portion” of his spirit, Elisha’s unwavering faith and vigilance secured the promised anointing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Paul (2 Corinthians 12; Philippians 4):&lt;/strong&gt; Paul learned that divine strength suffices amid weakness; his repeated pleadings led to a revelation that God’s grace was his power source, transforming his ministry and endurance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Revival Leaders:&lt;/strong&gt; Figures like J. B. Taylor, A. Mahan, and Madame Guyon illustrate that focused, persistent prayer, reading, and meditation on holiness precede a life‑changing baptism that fuels ministry and personal sanctification.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;An Unknown Woman:&lt;/strong&gt; In humble domestic circumstances, a single‑minded pursuit of God—reading, prayer, and reflection amid chores—resulted in such a radiant transformation that skeptics and infidels alike were won over by her testimony.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Principle Lessons&lt;/strong&gt;
1. &lt;strong&gt;Seek with All Your Heart:&lt;/strong&gt; God’s promise—“You will find Me when you search for Me with all your heart”—underscores that incomplete or half‑hearted seeking yields no lasting result.
2. &lt;strong&gt;Persist Until It Comes:&lt;/strong&gt; Impatience or unbelief that causes one to give up will forestall the blessing. True waiting involves active, expectant perseverance.
3. &lt;strong&gt;Value the Indwelling Spirit:&lt;/strong&gt; Recognizing the Spirit’s presence as the believer’s supreme treasure motivates unwavering pursuit and faithful stewardship of God’s gifts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Conclusion&lt;/strong&gt;
The baptism of the Spirit is not a ritual formality but the culmination of a deeply conditioned heart: awakened to need, confident in Christ’s fullness, resolved in desire, and steadfast in expectancy. All who truly seek this heavenly gift, prepared in mind and heart, will receive its empowering presence and fulfill their calling.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Books"></category><category term="Book-Summaries"></category><category term="Books"></category><category term="Chapter-Summaries"></category></entry><entry><title>Baptisms of the Spirit Under the Old and New Dispensations – a Condensed Overview</title><link href="https://preserving-holiness.github.io/baptisms-of-the-spirit-under-the-old-and-new-dispensations-a-condensed-overview.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2025-07-12T14:49:00-04:00</published><updated>2025-07-12T14:49:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Asa Mahan &amp; ChatGPT</name></author><id>tag:preserving-holiness.github.io,2025-07-12:/baptisms-of-the-spirit-under-the-old-and-new-dispensations-a-condensed-overview.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Introduction: Joel’s prophecy (Joel 2:28–29) foretells a universal outpouring of the Spirit; John clarifies that the Holy Spirit’s full gift awaited Christ’s glorification (John 7:39). Old Testament Baptisms: - Enoch and Early Saints: In varying degrees, individuals like Enoch enjoyed communion with God’s Spirit. - Abraham and Jacob: Each experienced...&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Introduction:&lt;/strong&gt;
Joel’s prophecy (Joel 2:28–29) foretells a universal outpouring of the Spirit; John clarifies that the Holy Spirit’s full gift awaited Christ’s glorification (John 7:39).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Old Testament Baptisms:&lt;/strong&gt;
- &lt;strong&gt;Enoch and Early Saints:&lt;/strong&gt; In varying degrees, individuals like Enoch enjoyed communion with God’s Spirit.
- &lt;strong&gt;Abraham and Jacob:&lt;/strong&gt; Each experienced transformative encounters (e.g., Abraham’s assured faith in God’s promise; Jacob’s vision at Bethel).
- &lt;strong&gt;Moses:&lt;/strong&gt; Exchanged the Spirit’s power for intimate knowledge of God’s character—Moses’ radiant face after Sinai marks a new inward communion.
- &lt;strong&gt;Seventy Elders:&lt;/strong&gt; God shared Moses’ Spirit so they could prophesy—true prophecy flows from the Spirit’s illumination, not merely future-telling (Numbers 11).
- &lt;strong&gt;Saul and Others:&lt;/strong&gt; Kings, prophets, even unlikely recipients (Saul, Saul’s messengers, Balaam) received temporary Spirit-baptisms that conferred speaking God’s truth and specific gifts.
- &lt;strong&gt;Elisha:&lt;/strong&gt; A lasting double portion of Elijah’s Spirit inaugurated his prophetic ministry (2 Kings 2).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;New Testament Precursors:&lt;/strong&gt;
- &lt;strong&gt;Zacharias, Elizabeth, Mary:&lt;/strong&gt; Each filled with the Holy Spirit before Pentecost, echoing Old Testament patterns but pointing ahead to greater realities (Luke 1).
- These experiences included joy, prophecy, magnifying God, and foreshadowed Pentecost’s power.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Great Difference:&lt;/strong&gt;
1. &lt;strong&gt;Universality:&lt;/strong&gt; Old anointings were rare and for individuals; New promises the Spirit to &lt;em&gt;all&lt;/em&gt; believers (Joel’s “all flesh,” Acts 2).
2. &lt;strong&gt;Permanency:&lt;/strong&gt; Once temporary, now an abiding Comforter who remains with the Church (John 14:16).
3. &lt;strong&gt;Greater Power:&lt;/strong&gt; Old saints saw partial glories; Christ’s life and resurrection fully reveal God’s character. The Spirit now unveils Christ’s glory in us, bringing life, sanctification, and joy beyond earlier experiences.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Scriptural Testimony:&lt;/strong&gt;
- &lt;strong&gt;Peter:&lt;/strong&gt; Prophets longed to know the Spirit’s timing—Pentecost fulfilled their prophecies (1 Peter 1:10–12).
- &lt;strong&gt;Hebrews:&lt;/strong&gt; Old saints received promises by faith but awaited our fuller blessings (Hebrews 11:39–40).
- &lt;strong&gt;John:&lt;/strong&gt; The Spirit in its New Testament fullness was not yet given until after Christ’s glorification (John 7:39).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Implications for Today:&lt;/strong&gt;
- Believers now enjoy Spirit-baptisms equal to or surpassing the highest Old Testament experiences.
- The Church’s weakness stems from ignorance or neglect of Spirit-filled living.
- Restoring this doctrine and practice will usher in revival and prepare for the millennium.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Vision of the Future:&lt;/strong&gt;
Ezekiel’s river of life (Ezekiel 47) symbolizes the ever-growing, life-giving power of the Spirit in the Church, promising a golden age yet to come.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Conclusion:&lt;/strong&gt;
The Old and New Testament baptisms share a divine illumination and power, but the New dispensation’s gift of the Spirit—universal, permanent, and supremely powerful in Christ’s light—marks a transformative era for the Church. May every believer experience this all-empowering baptism. Amen.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Books"></category><category term="Book-Summaries"></category><category term="Books"></category><category term="Chapter-Summaries"></category></entry><entry><title>Doctrine of the Baptism of the Holy Ghost</title><link href="https://preserving-holiness.github.io/doctrine-of-the-baptism-of-the-holy-ghost.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2025-07-12T14:30:00-04:00</published><updated>2025-07-12T14:30:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Asa Mahan &amp; ChatGPT</name></author><id>tag:preserving-holiness.github.io,2025-07-12:/doctrine-of-the-baptism-of-the-holy-ghost.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Key Scripture Passages - Acts 19:1–6: Paul meets believers in Ephesus who haven’t heard of the Holy Ghost. After baptism in Jesus’ name and laying on of hands, they receive the Spirit, speak in tongues, and prophesy. - Acts 8:14–17: Peter and John pray for Samaritan believers to receive the...&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Key Scripture Passages&lt;/strong&gt;
- &lt;strong&gt;Acts 19:1–6&lt;/strong&gt;: Paul meets believers in Ephesus who haven’t heard of the Holy Ghost. After baptism in Jesus’ name and laying on of hands, they receive the Spirit, speak in tongues, and prophesy.
- &lt;strong&gt;Acts 8:14–17&lt;/strong&gt;: Peter and John pray for Samaritan believers to receive the Holy Ghost after baptism.
- &lt;strong&gt;Acts 10:44–47&lt;/strong&gt;: The Holy Ghost falls on Gentile listeners in Cornelius’ house; they speak in tongues and praise God.
- &lt;strong&gt;Ephesians 1:13–14; 3:14–21&lt;/strong&gt;: After believing, Christians are sealed with the Spirit as a guarantee of their inheritance and are strengthened in their inner being to know Christ’s love and fullness.
- &lt;strong&gt;John 7:38–39&lt;/strong&gt;: Believers receive the Spirit after Christ’s glorification, symbolized by rivers of living water.
- &lt;strong&gt;1 Corinthians 12&lt;/strong&gt;: The Spirit gives varied gifts—wisdom, healing, prophecy, tongues—to build up the Church.
- &lt;strong&gt;Acts 2 (Pentecost)&lt;/strong&gt;: The apostles unite in prayer, experience visible signs (wind, tongues), and are filled with the Spirit, speaking God’s word boldly.
- &lt;strong&gt;John 14–16&lt;/strong&gt;: Jesus promises another Helper (Comforter) who will dwell with believers forever, empowering and guiding them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Main Lessons&lt;/strong&gt;
1. &lt;strong&gt;Occurs After Conversion&lt;/strong&gt;: The Holy Ghost is given &lt;em&gt;after&lt;/em&gt; a person believes, completing their qualification for Christian service.
2. &lt;strong&gt;Empowers Believers&lt;/strong&gt;: This baptism equips Christians for tasks beyond natural ability—prayer, witness, endurance.
3. &lt;strong&gt;Visible Change&lt;/strong&gt;: Recipients and observers notice a distinct transformation—new boldness, spiritual gifts, praise.
4. &lt;strong&gt;Sought by Faith&lt;/strong&gt;: The Spirit is not automatic at conversion but promised to all who genuinely seek and wait in prayer.
5. &lt;strong&gt;Seal and Pledge&lt;/strong&gt;: The Spirit acts as God’s seal on believers, assuring them of forgiveness and inheritance until full redemption.
6. &lt;strong&gt;Fellowship and Fullness&lt;/strong&gt;: Through the Spirit, Christ and the Father dwell within, leading to deep fellowship, love, unity, joy, and peace.
7. &lt;strong&gt;Diverse Gifts&lt;/strong&gt;: Every believer receives spiritual gifts to serve the body of Christ; prophecy (spiritual truth) and tongues edify the Church.
8. &lt;strong&gt;Unity in the Church&lt;/strong&gt;: Baptism in the Spirit fosters unity and love, reflecting the oneness Jesus prayed for among his followers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Effects of the Baptism&lt;/strong&gt;
- &lt;strong&gt;Power&lt;/strong&gt;: Strength to pray, witness, and endure hardship ("run and not be weary").
- &lt;strong&gt;Insight&lt;/strong&gt;: Deeper understanding of Scripture and God’s truth.
- &lt;strong&gt;Assurance&lt;/strong&gt;: Conviction of sonship and eternal life ("we know we are of God").
- &lt;strong&gt;Fellowship&lt;/strong&gt;: Intimate communion with the Father, Son, and other believers.
- &lt;strong&gt;Joy and Peace&lt;/strong&gt;: Inner serenity, joy in trials, and hope that surpasses understanding.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Conditions to Receive&lt;/strong&gt;
1. &lt;strong&gt;Recognize the Promise&lt;/strong&gt;: Understand that this blessing is distinct from conversion, miracles, or other gifts.
2. &lt;strong&gt;Claim by Faith&lt;/strong&gt;: Believe firmly in God’s promise and righteousness through Jesus.
3. &lt;strong&gt;Seek Wholeheartedly&lt;/strong&gt;: Pray and wait in unity, like the early disciples at Pentecost.
4. &lt;strong&gt;Persevere&lt;/strong&gt;: Continue seeking until the Spirit fills the heart.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Conclusion&lt;/strong&gt;
The Baptism of the Holy Ghost is God’s highest gift in the New Covenant. It is essential for full Christian living, empowering believers with spiritual gifts, deep fellowship, and lasting change. Like the early Church, Christians today should understand, seek, and receive this promise to walk in the Spirit’s fullness.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Books"></category><category term="Book-Summaries"></category><category term="Books"></category><category term="Chapter-Summaries"></category></entry><entry><title>Christ’s Experience and Teachings on the Baptism of the Holy Ghost</title><link href="https://preserving-holiness.github.io/christs-experience-and-teachings-on-the-baptism-of-the-holy-ghost.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2025-07-12T13:57:00-04:00</published><updated>2025-07-12T13:57:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Asa Mahan &amp; ChatGPT</name></author><id>tag:preserving-holiness.github.io,2025-07-12:/christs-experience-and-teachings-on-the-baptism-of-the-holy-ghost.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;CHAPTER 2: CHRIST’S EXPERIENCE AND TEACHINGS ON THE BAPTISM OF THE HOLY GHOST 1. Divine and Human Forms in Christ - Jesus perfectly combined divine glory and human perfection: He is both our righteous Lord and our exemplar. - His spiritual life also depended on the Holy Spirit, just as...&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Divine and Human Forms in Christ&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Jesus perfectly combined divine glory and human perfection: He is both our righteous Lord and our exemplar.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;His spiritual life also depended on the Holy Spirit, just as ours does.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Prophetic Foundation&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Isaiah’s prophecies foretold that the Spirit would rest on the Messiah, granting wisdom, understanding, counsel, power, knowledge, and reverent awe (Isaiah 11:1–3; 42:1; 61:1).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These passages show Christ needed the Spirit’s anointing to fulfill His mission.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;New Testament Confirmation&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;John 3:34 emphasizes Christ’s speech and works came from the unlimited Spirit given to Him.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Christ’s frequent prayer and solitude reflect His dependence on divine power.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Christ’s Baptisms of the Spirit&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;At His baptism by John, Jesus prayed and received the Holy Spirit as a dove (Luke 3:21).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;After overcoming temptation, He returned “in the power of the Spirit” and began teaching boldly (Luke 4:14–15).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In Nazareth He read Isaiah 61, declared its fulfillment, and amazed the crowd by the Spirit’s power in His words.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Christ as Exemplar for Believers&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If even the sinless Son needed Spirit-baptism, we must likewise seek it before doing God’s work.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Christ asked the Father for the Spirit, showing us to ask, seek, and wait for “power from on high.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Christ’s Teaching on the Spirit&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Seek and Receive&lt;/strong&gt;: "Ask, seek, knock"—God gives the Holy Spirit to those who earnestly ask (Luke 11:9–13).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Personal Presence&lt;/strong&gt;: The Spirit is not mere influence but a permanent, personal Comforter abiding within believers (John 14:16–17).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Greater Blessings&lt;/strong&gt;: Believers receive richer gifts and understanding through the Spirit than through Christ’s earthly ministry (John 7:38–39).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Spirit’s Mission&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The Spirit teaches, reminds, guides into truth, glorifies Christ, testifies of Jesus, reproves the world, and reveals future things (John 14–16).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Through the Spirit we know God and Christ intimately, are transformed into Christ’s likeness, and bear spiritual fruit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Promises Through the Spirit&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Answered Prayer&lt;/strong&gt;: In Jesus’ name we may ask anything and receive it so joy may be full (John 16:23–24).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Divine Indwelling&lt;/strong&gt;: Father, Son, and Spirit dwell in us, uniting us with God (John 14:23; 17:21–23).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Peace and Joy&lt;/strong&gt;: We share Christ’s peace and joy as the Spirit abides in us (John 14:27; 17:13).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Greater Works&lt;/strong&gt;: Believers, empowered by the Spirit, will do even greater works than Jesus did (John 14:12).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Church’s Mission and Unity&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;All believers, as a Spirit-anointed body, are sent to labor for world salvation.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Each receives a special baptism of power for their unique mission, and together exhibits unity, love, and divine power that convinces the world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Christ’s Final Commission&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;After rising, Jesus breathed the Spirit on His disciples, commanded them to wait in Jerusalem for Spirit baptism, and then sent them out to preach with power (John 20:22; Acts 1:4–8).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Believers must both go in Christ’s name and tarry until they receive the Spirit’s power.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Key Takeaway:&lt;/strong&gt;
Jesus, though divine, modeled for us the need to seek and depend on the Holy Spirit. Through prophetic promise and His own teaching and example, He shows that Spirit-baptism is essential for empowering, guiding, and transforming believers to finish God’s work and bear witness to the world.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Books"></category><category term="Book-Summaries"></category><category term="Books"></category><category term="Chapter-Summaries"></category></entry><entry><title>God’s Pattern and the Path to Christian Character</title><link href="https://preserving-holiness.github.io/gods-pattern-and-the-path-to-christian-character.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2025-07-12T13:48:00-04:00</published><updated>2025-07-12T13:48:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Asa Mahan and ChatGPT</name></author><id>tag:preserving-holiness.github.io,2025-07-12:/gods-pattern-and-the-path-to-christian-character.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Scriptural Foundation Jesus promised that all who believe in Him would receive the Holy Spirit, making their lives overflow with spiritual power (John 7:37–39). Paul contrasted righteousness by faith with striving through law (Romans 9:30–32), showing that true growth depends on faith and the Spirit, not our own efforts. God’s...&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Scriptural Foundation&lt;/strong&gt;
Jesus promised that all who believe in Him would receive the Holy Spirit, making their lives overflow with spiritual power (John 7:37–39). Paul contrasted righteousness by faith with striving through law (Romans 9:30–32), showing that true growth depends on faith and the Spirit, not our own efforts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;God’s Divine Pattern&lt;/strong&gt;
Scripture outlines a clear model for the Christian character, called the “new man,” replacing our old, unrenewed nature:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Cleansed and Redeemed:&lt;/strong&gt; Freed from sin and idols, like the prophetic vision of eternal light and unending joy (cf. Isaiah, Joel’s outpouring).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Transformed by Glory:&lt;/strong&gt; Reflecting God’s image, growing from one level of glory to the next, filled with Christ’s love (2 Corinthians, Ephesians).  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Living in Fellowship:&lt;/strong&gt; Walking in God’s light, perfecting love, enjoying continual communion with Father and Son.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Empowered by the Spirit:&lt;/strong&gt; Joyful prayer, rivers of living water, strength in weakness, conquering all trials (Galatians, Romans).  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Spiritual Victory:&lt;/strong&gt; Growing faith and love, exercising power with God and people, shining as light and salt to the world.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This new life is not our achievement but God’s design—every trait springs from His Spirit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Source of True Transformation&lt;/strong&gt;
Every vital trait of the new man—vision of glory, fellowship with God, assurance of hope, love, joy, peace, spiritual victory—comes from the Holy Spirit:&lt;br&gt;
- He reveals Christ, testifies we are children of God, intercedes in prayer, and produces His fruit in us (Romans, Galatians).&lt;br&gt;
- He enables us to put off old habits and put on Christlike character by His power (Romans 8, Galatians 5).&lt;br&gt;
- Rivers of living water refer directly to the Spirit’s outpouring (John 7:39).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Order of God’s Work in the Believer&lt;/strong&gt;
1. &lt;strong&gt;Conviction and Faith:&lt;/strong&gt; The Spirit convicts us of sin, brings repentance, and leads us to trust Christ—this begins justification.&lt;br&gt;
2. &lt;strong&gt;Receiving the Spirit:&lt;/strong&gt; After believing, we are invited to ask for and receive the Spirit’s fullness. Apostles prayed that new believers might receive this powerful baptism (Acts 8:14–17; 19:1–6).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Seeking the Spirit in Faith&lt;/strong&gt;
Just as sinners ask for forgiveness, believers must ask God in faith for the Spirit’s fullness: “How much more will your Father give the Holy Spirit to those who ask Him!” (Luke 11:13). Jesus told His disciples to remain in Jerusalem until they were clothed with power from on high (Luke 24:49; Acts 1:4–8).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Consequences of Neglect&lt;/strong&gt;
Without this Spirit-baptism, Christian life falls short:&lt;br&gt;
- It remains powerless and hesitant, unable to reflect God’s pattern fully.&lt;br&gt;
- Historical examples: The twelve at Ephesus and Apollos were fervent believers but lacked fullness until they received the Spirit, limiting their impact (Acts 19; 18).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Two Views Compared&lt;/strong&gt;
1. &lt;strong&gt;Instantaneous at Conversion:&lt;/strong&gt; All the Spirit’s presence and power arrive at new birth.&lt;br&gt;
2. &lt;strong&gt;Distinct Promise after Belief:&lt;/strong&gt; Conversion brings initial indwelling; full empowerment comes afterward by asking in faith.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Why This Matters&lt;/strong&gt;
Teaching that nothing more is needed after salvation deprives believers of power, joy, and assurance. Misleading instruction sends them chasing shadows instead of seeking God’s promised fullness. Pastors and teachers must guide the flock to the clear word: ask, wait, and receive the promised baptism of the Spirit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;A Call to Seek&lt;/strong&gt;
This chapter aims to help readers know God’s pattern and attain it. If you have believed but never asked for the Spirit’s fullness, discover the better thing God offers. Read on, pray, and receive until filled with all the fullness of God.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Books"></category><category term="Book-Summaries"></category><category term="Books"></category><category term="Chapter-Summaries"></category></entry><entry><title>How to Cultivate the Spirit’s Companionship</title><link href="https://preserving-holiness.github.io/how-to-cultivate-the-spirits-companionship.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2025-07-12T13:04:00-04:00</published><updated>2025-07-12T13:04:00-04:00</updated><author><name>A W Tozer &amp; ChatGPT</name></author><id>tag:preserving-holiness.github.io,2025-07-12:/how-to-cultivate-the-spirits-companionship.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;“Can two walk together, except they be agreed?” — Amos 3:3 True fellowship with the Holy Spirit requires wholehearted agreement—an intentional, personal commitment to walk with Him daily. Many believers enjoy the benefits of salvation but hesitate to surrender fully, treating faith...&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Can two walk together, except they be agreed?” — Amos 3:3&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;True fellowship with the Holy Spirit requires wholehearted agreement—an intentional, personal commitment to walk with Him daily. Many believers enjoy the benefits of salvation but hesitate to surrender fully, treating faith like insurance rather than an intimate journey. This chapter calls those prepared—whose hearts long for heaven’s pull—to deepen their relationship with the Spirit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;1. Recognize the Spirit as a Living Person&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Holy Spirit is God’s third Person, capable of personal fellowship. Like any relationship, it grows through mutual engagement and affection.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;2. Be Engrossed with Jesus Christ&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Only when Jesus is glorified in your life will the Spirit overflow within you. Honor Christ by trusting, obeying, and glorifying Him fully; as you exalt Jesus, the Spirit responds with intimacy and power.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;3. Walk in Righteousness&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;True spirituality is inseparable from right living. Deny ungodliness, honor others, and maintain integrity. Fellowship with the Holy Spirit cannot thrive amid unholy behavior.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;4. Make Your Thoughts a Clean Sanctuary&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Your mind is the Spirit’s dwelling place. Choose thoughts of peace, charity, and holiness. Purge unclean ideas so your inner life reflects the beauty of God’s presence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;5. Seek Him in the Word&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Bible is the Spirit’s inspired revelation. Meditate deeply—without distractions—letting Scripture illuminate your heart. Replace superficial study with prayerful reflection on God’s Word.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;6. Cultivate the Art of Awareness&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Learn to recognize the Spirit’s presence in every moment: over breakfast, during work, or in quiet prayer. Like befriending a newborn, invest time daily. Soon even mundane tasks become sacred as Christ’s life flows through you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This summary preserves the heart of the original message while making it accessible.]&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Books"></category><category term="Book-Summaries"></category><category term="Books"></category><category term="Chapter-Summaries"></category></entry><entry><title>Preparing Your Heart for the Holy Spirit</title><link href="https://preserving-holiness.github.io/preparing-your-heart-for-the-holy-spirit.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2025-07-12T12:58:00-04:00</published><updated>2025-07-12T12:58:00-04:00</updated><author><name>A W Tozer &amp; ChatGPT</name></author><id>tag:preserving-holiness.github.io,2025-07-12:/preparing-your-heart-for-the-holy-spirit.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Claim Your Birthright - The Spirit-filled life is not optional or for a select few. When Christ died, this fullness became available to every believer. 2. Welcome Him as Friend, Not Foe -...&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Claim Your Birthright&lt;/strong&gt;  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Spirit-filled life is not optional or for a select few. When Christ died, this fullness became available to every believer.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Welcome Him as Friend, Not Foe&lt;/strong&gt;  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Holy Spirit isn’t strange or scary. He’s Jesus’ presence in you—gentle, loving, and good.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Surrender Everything&lt;/strong&gt;  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s not just about blessings. Are you ready to let go of your plans, pride, and control? True filling requires handing over every area of life.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Long for More Than Basics&lt;/strong&gt;  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Prayers, Bible study, and good deeds are vital—but they’re just the start. Crave deeper fellowship, purity, strength for service, and victory over temptation.  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Steps to Receive the Holy Spirit&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Offer Your Whole Self&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
   Present your body, thoughts, emotions, and will to God as an act of worship (Rom. 12:1–2).  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ask in Faith&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
   Simple, believing prayer is enough: “Ask, and it will be given you” (Luke 11:9–13).  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Live in Obedience&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
   The Spirit is promised to those who follow Christ’s commands (Acts 5:32).  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Trust His Promise&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
   Just as you received salvation by faith, receive the Spirit’s fullness the same way (Gal. 3:2).  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you believe it’s your right, yearn for His fullness, and take these steps with simple trust, the Holy Spirit will come and fill you. Tonight, as we sing “The Comforter Has Come,” open your heart, ask, and expect Him to move.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Books"></category><category term="Book-Summaries"></category><category term="Books"></category><category term="Chapter-Summaries"></category></entry><entry><title>The Promise of the Father: A Condensed Reflection</title><link href="https://preserving-holiness.github.io/the-promise-of-the-father.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2025-07-12T12:54:00-04:00</published><updated>2025-07-12T12:54:00-04:00</updated><author><name>A W Tozer and ChatGPT</name></author><id>tag:preserving-holiness.github.io,2025-07-12:/the-promise-of-the-father.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Opening Promise Jesus tells His disciples in Luke 24:49, "I send the promise of my Father upon you," pointing back to Joel's prophecy that God would pour out His Spirit on all people. Three Stages of the Promise 1. Promise Phase (John the Baptist to Resurrection) - Disciples knew Jesus...&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Opening Promise&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
Jesus tells His disciples in Luke 24:49, "I send the promise of my Father upon you," pointing back to Joel's prophecy that God would pour out His Spirit on all people.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Three Stages of the Promise&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
1. &lt;strong&gt;Promise Phase (John the Baptist to Resurrection)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
   - Disciples knew Jesus personally—His teachings, death, and resurrection.&lt;br&gt;
   - Jesus built their hope for a new power beyond what they already experienced.&lt;br&gt;
   - They expected an "outpouring" of divine energy they had not yet seen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Preparation Phase (Resurrection to Pentecost)&lt;/strong&gt;  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;After rising, Jesus commanded the disciples to "tarry" in Jerusalem.  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Their work paused so they could receive what had been promised.  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Though seemingly idle, they grew in unity and expectation, gathering 120 believers in prayer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Realization Phase (Pentecost)&lt;/strong&gt;  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The Holy Spirit arrived like a rushing wind and tongues of fire (Acts 2).  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Peter describes this as God "shedding forth" the Spirit—an overflow beyond their hopes.  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Believers gained new, inner proof of faith: the Spirit's direct witness in their hearts.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;External vs. Internal Evidence&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
- &lt;strong&gt;External Proofs&lt;/strong&gt;: Scriptures, John the Baptist’s testimony, God’s miracles, and Christ’s works all point to Jesus but rely on logic and outside signs.&lt;br&gt;
- &lt;strong&gt;Internal Witness&lt;/strong&gt;: Only the Holy Spirit gives an immediate, living assurance—like feeling alive—free from the need for argument.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Impact of the Holy Spirit&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
- &lt;strong&gt;Transformation&lt;/strong&gt;: Converts in distant lands, unfamiliar with Christian logic, believe and change by the Spirit’s power alone.&lt;br&gt;
- &lt;strong&gt;Emotion and Joy&lt;/strong&gt;: Early believers experienced vibrant emotion and spiritual delight, qualities lacking in many modern services.&lt;br&gt;
- &lt;strong&gt;Authority&lt;/strong&gt;: Freed from fear and doubt, they spoke with boldness rooted in life, not mere logic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ongoing Promise Today&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
Some claim the Spirit’s coming was a one-time event only for the first church. But if the fullness received by the apostles doesn’t apply to us, it’s like eating Peter’s meal in A.D. 33 and expecting it to nourish us now—impossible across centuries and seas.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Questions for Reflection&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
- Is the Father’s promise solely for first-century Christians, or must each believer be filled today?&lt;br&gt;
- Does "the new birth" and Spirit’s fullness happen once for all, or must we personally receive them?&lt;br&gt;
- Do we have what the early Church enjoyed, or have our expectations fallen short?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;A Call to Seek&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
Jesus urged His followers to wait because the Spirit’s coming would mean the difference between failure and success. The early Church said, "They were amazed," because God gave more than He promised.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Invitation&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
If today’s faith feels weaker than what was promised, admit the gap. Seek Scripture, prayer, obedience, and faith so that the Father’s promise may be yours in full—beyond expectation, just as in the first Pentecost.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Books"></category><category term="Book-Summaries"></category><category term="Books"></category><category term="Chapter-Summaries"></category></entry><entry><title>[Who Is the Holy Spirit?]</title><link href="https://preserving-holiness.github.io/who-is-the-holy-spirit.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2025-07-09T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2025-07-09T00:00:00-04:00</updated><author><name>A W Tozer and ChatGPT</name></author><id>tag:preserving-holiness.github.io,2025-07-09:/who-is-the-holy-spirit.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;--- &lt;strong&gt;Chapter 1: Who Is the Holy Spirit? (Abridged)&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;strong&gt;1. Defining “Spirit”&lt;/strong&gt; When we speak of spirit here, we aren’t talking about courage, temperament, or energy. Spirit is real—another mode of being, just as real as matter. While matter has weight, shape, and occupies space, spirit can penetrate everything—bodies, thoughts,...&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Chapter 1: Who Is the Holy Spirit? (Abridged)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;1. Defining “Spirit”&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
When we speak of spirit here, we aren’t talking about courage, temperament, or energy. Spirit is real—another mode of being, just as real as matter. While matter has weight, shape, and occupies space, spirit can penetrate everything—bodies, thoughts, even other spirit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2. What Is the Holy Spirit?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
The Holy Spirit is a divine Being existing in this same nonmaterial mode. No weight, size, or color—but no less real. He is not mere enthusiasm, genius, or inspiration. He is a Person: with will, intelligence, feeling, and the power to love, hear, and speak.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;3. Biblical and Historical Witness&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
- &lt;strong&gt;Creeds:&lt;/strong&gt; The Nicene Creed (AD 325) calls Him “Lord and Giver of life” to be worshiped with Father and Son. The Athanasian Creed repeats: “Such as the Father is, such is the Holy Ghost,” implying equality with the other Persons of the Trinity.
- &lt;strong&gt;Hymns:&lt;/strong&gt; Writers pray to the Holy Ghost with divine titles: “power divine,” “cleanse this guilty heart,” “reign supreme.” Such prayers can only be addressed to God.
- &lt;strong&gt;Scripture:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
  - &lt;strong&gt;Omnipresence:&lt;/strong&gt; “Whither shall I go from Your Spirit?” (Psalm 139:7) – only God is everywhere.&lt;br&gt;
  - &lt;strong&gt;Eternity:&lt;/strong&gt; Hebrews 9:14 speaks of the “eternal Spirit,” a quality no created being has.&lt;br&gt;
  - &lt;strong&gt;Baptismal Formula:&lt;/strong&gt; Matthew 28:19 instructs baptism “in the name of the Father, Son, and Holy Spirit,” placing the Spirit on equal footing with God.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;4. Why It Matters&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
Many Christians accept the doctrine of the Spirit without knowing or experiencing His power. Truths can lie dormant if we don’t teach and apply them. Just as belief in healing does little unless practiced, belief in the Spirit’s fullness does little unless we seek it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;5. What the Spirit Is Like&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
Everywhere, always present—He is indistinguishable in character from the Father and the Son. If Jesus walked among us today, we’d feel welcome, loved, safe. That is the Spirit: the same love, kindness, and warmth we find in Christ.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Invitation&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
Believe not just in doctrine but in living reality. Invite the Holy Spirit to fill your heart, transforming you from within with divine presence, power, and peace.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Books"></category><category term="Book-Summaries"></category><category term="Books"></category><category term="Chapter-Summaries"></category></entry><entry><title>Preface to How to be Filled with the Holy Spirit, by A. W. Tozer</title><link href="https://preserving-holiness.github.io/preface-to-how-to-be-filled-with-the-holy-spirit-by-a-w-tozer.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2025-07-05T18:58:00-04:00</published><updated>2025-07-05T18:58:00-04:00</updated><author><name>A. W. Tozer &amp; Gemini 2.5 Flash</name></author><id>tag:preserving-holiness.github.io,2025-07-05:/preface-to-how-to-be-filled-with-the-holy-spirit-by-a-w-tozer.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Preface to the Book.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Title: Preface to How to be Filled with the Holy Spirit, by A. W. Tozer
Date: 2025-07-05
Status: published
Category: Books
Tags: Books, Book-Summaries, Chapter-Summaries
Author: A. W. Tozer &amp;amp; Gemini 2.5 Flash
Summary: Preface to the Book.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Understanding the Holy Spirit&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This book, published by Moody Publishers, is a collection of sermons on the Holy Spirit.  Authored by A.W.T., it aims to guide believers towards a deeper understanding and relationship with the Holy Spirit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Key Features:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Content:&lt;/strong&gt; The book explores the identity of the Holy Spirit, the promise of the Father, how to be filled with the Holy Spirit, and how to cultivate a deeper companionship with Him.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Style:&lt;/strong&gt; Written in a conversational, informal style reflecting its origins as a series of sermons.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Purpose:&lt;/strong&gt; To help Christian believers develop a closer relationship with the Holy Spirit.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Copyright:&lt;/strong&gt; © 1952, 1992, 2001, 2016 by Moody Bible Institute of Chicago.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;ISBN:&lt;/strong&gt; 978-1-60066-799-2&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The proceeds from the book support Moody Bible Institute students.  The author notes that the book's informal style is a result of its sermon origins.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Books"></category><category term="Books"></category><category term="Book-Summaries"></category><category term="Chapter-Summaries"></category></entry></feed>